普罗米修斯从众神那里偷了火种 并将其交给人类
为此 他被锁在一块岩石上 受到永恒的折磨
奥本海默博士
Dr.Oppenheimer.
1. 分裂
奥本海默博士
Dr.Oppenheimer.
在我们开始前 你要宣读一份声明
As we begin, I believe you have a statement to read into the record.
是的 法官大人
Yes, Your Honor.
我们不是法官 博士  -对
We're not judges, Doctor.
当然不是
No. Of course.
各位安全委员会成员
Members of the security board.
你们对我做出所谓的诋毁性指控
The so-called and derogatory information in your indictment of me
无法受到公正评断
cannot be fairly understood,
除非真正理解我的生活和工作
except in the context of my life and my work.
他作证了多久？
How long did he testify?
2. 融合
老实说 我忘了
Honestly, I forget.
整场听证会耗时一个月
The whole hearing took a month.
真是一场折磨
An ordeal.
我只看过庭审记录
I've only read the transcripts, but...
谁会想为自己的一生辩护？
Who'd want to justify their whole life?
你不在场？
You weren't there?
身为主席 我不被允许出席
-As chairman, I wasn't allowed to be.
他们真的会问那件事？
Are they really going to ask about it?
那是好几年前的事  -四年前…
It was years ago. Four years ago.
五年前
-Five.
奥本海默仍然分裂着美国
Oppenheimer still divides America.
委员会想知道你的立场
The committee is gonna want to know where you stood.
瑟蒙参议员不希望你觉得是你在受审
Senator Thurmond asked me to say not to feel that you're on trial.
你刚刚说了我才这么觉得
Aw.Funny, I didn't till you just said that.
史特劳斯先生…  -是少将
Really, Mr.Strauss-- It's Admiral.
史特劳斯少将 这只是走程序
Admiral Strauss.This is a formality.
艾森豪总统请你加入他的内阁
President Eisenhower has asked you to be in his cabinet.
参议院别无选择只能确认
Senate really has no choice but to confirm you.
如果他们提起奥本海默？
And if they bring up Oppenheimer?
若是如此 你就据实回答
When they bring up Oppenheimer, you answer honestly.
参议员无法否认你尽了职责
No senator can deny you did your duty.
那会很难堪
It'll be uncomfortable.
谁会想为自己的一生辩护？
Who'd want to justify their whole life?
你为何离开美国？
Why did you leave the United States?
我想学习新物理学
I, uh--I wanted to study the new physics.
不能在美国学习？
Was there nowhere here?
伯克利有首屈一指的理论物理学系
I thought Berkeley had the leading theoretical physics department.
我成立了以后就有
Yes.Once I had built it.
但我得先去欧洲
But first I had to go to Europe.
我在剑桥大学的导师是帕特里克·布莱克特
I went to Cambridge to study under Patrick Blackett.
你在那里比在美国更快乐？
Were you happier there than in America?
更快乐？  -对
Happier?  -Yes.
并没有 我…
No. No, I, uh...
我很想家
I was homesick, um,
感情不成熟
emotionally immature,
受到一个隐藏宇宙的幻象困扰
troubled by visions of a hidden universe.
我在实验室一无是处
Useless in the lab.
天啊 奥本海默
Christ, Oppenheimer.
你有没有睡觉？
Have you had any sleep?
再来一次
Start again.
我得去听课 先生
I need to go to the lecture, sir.
为什么？
Why?
讲师是尼尔斯·波耳
It's Niels Bohr.
我完全忘了
I'd completely forgot.
好吧 我们去吧
All right.Let's go.
你不能去 奥本海默
Oh, no, not you, Oppenheimer.
你要涂覆那些平板
You finish coating those plates.
氰化钾
量子物理学不是向前迈进的科学
Quantum physics is not a step forward.
而是一种理解现实的全新方法
It is a new way to understand reality.
爱因斯坦打开一扇门 我们通过它窥探
Einstein's opened the door. Now we are peering through,
看到一个全新的世界
seeing a world inside our world.
充满能量与悖论 不是每个人都能接受
A world of energy and paradox that not everyone can accept.
绝对是如此
Yeah--
你没事吧？
Are you all right?
尼尔斯 这是 J·罗伯特·奥本海默
Niels, meet J.Robert Oppenheimer.
“ J”是什么的缩写？
What's the J stand for?
什么都不是
Nothing, apparently.
你听了我的讲课 只有你问了好问题
You were at my lecture.You asked the only good question.
他的确独具见解
No one's denying his insight.
但在实验室的表现有点差强人意
It's his laboratory work that leaves a little to be desired.
我听过同样的讲课…  -在哈佛
I heard you give the same lectu--
你问了同样的问题
At Harvard, yes, and you asked the same question.
为什么再问一次？
Why ask again?
我不喜欢你的回答
Hadn't liked your answer.
昨天的回答有好一些吗？
Did you like it better yesterday?
好很多
-A lot.
你抬起石头却没想到会出现一条毒蛇
You can lift the stone without being ready for the snake that's revealed.
现在看来你准备好了
Now it seems you're ready.
但你不喜欢进实验室？
But you don't enjoy the lab?
那就离开剑桥大学的实验室
So get out of Cambridge with its beakers and potions.
去能让你思考的地方
Go somewhere they'll let you think.
去哪里？
Where?
哥廷根大学
Göttingen.
玻恩？  -玻恩
Born.  -Born.
前往德国师从马克斯·玻恩
Get to Germany.Study under Max Born.
学习理论方法
Learn the ways of theory.
我会捎个口信
I'll send word.
有虫子
Wormhole.
你的数学好不好？
How's your mathematics?
对他想当的物理学家还不够好
Not good enough for the physicist he wants to be.
代数就像乐谱
Algebra's like sheet music.
重点不是你会不会读音乐？
The important thing isn't "can you read music?"
而是能不能听到？你能听到音乐吗？
It's "can you hear it?" Can you hear the music, Robert?
我能听到
Yes, I can.
《荒原》T. S. 艾略特
史特拉汶斯基
来自怀俄明州的参议员
The senator from Wyoming.
史特劳斯少将…
Admiral Strauss,
我想知道你和罗伯特·奥本海默的关系
I'm interested in your relationship with Dr.J.Robert Oppenheimer.
你在1947年认识他？
You met him in 1947?
没错
Correct.
你当时是原子能委员会主席？
You were commissioner of the Atomic Energy Commission?
是的 但我认识罗伯特的时候是…
I was, but I actually met Robert in my capacity as board member
普林斯顿高等研究院理事会成员
of the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton,
他在战后是举世闻名的物理界巨擘
because after the war he was world renowned as the great man of physics,
我决心要请他担任院长
and I was determined to get him to run the Institute.
计程车
奥本海默博士 幸会了
Dr.Oppenheimer.An honor.
史特劳斯先生
Mr.Strauss.
应该念成 “史劳斯”
It's pronounced "straws."
欧本海默 奥本海默…
Oh-ppenheimer, Oppenheimer.
不管怎么念都是犹太人
Whatever way you say it, they know I'm Jewish.
我是曼哈顿以马内利会堂的主席
I'm president of Temple Emanu-El in Manhattan.
“史劳斯” 只是南方的发音
"Straws" is just the Southern pronunciation.
欢迎来到研究院 你在这里会很开心
Anyway, welcome to the Institute. I think you could be very happy here.
而且通勤很方便
Yes, well, you'll love the commute.
那栋房子是给你和尊夫人住的…
The position comes with that house for you and your wife,
还有两个小孩？
and your--Is it two children?
对 两个
Yes, two.
我非常崇拜你的研究成果
I'm a great admirer of your work.
你也是物理学家吗 史劳斯先生？
And you're a physicist by training, Mr.Strauss?
抱歉 休息室下午四点有茶点
I'm sorry, common room, four o'clock tea.
不 我没念过什么书 完全是白手起家
No, I'm not trained in physics or anything else. I'm a self-made man.
我能理解  -真的吗？
Ah.I can relate to that.Really?
是的 我父亲也一样
Yes, my father was one.
这会是你的办公室
And this would be your office.
听说他下午多半都会在那里
I'm told he's there most afternoons.
我很好奇你为何没让他参与曼哈顿计划
You know, I've always wondered why you didn't involve him in the Manhattan Project.
我们这个时代最伟大的科学家
Greatest scientific mind of our time.
他那个时代
Of his time.
爱因斯坦在40年多前发表相对论
Einstein published his Theory of Relativity more than 40 years ago now.
却从未接受它揭露的量子世界
But never embraced the quantum world it revealed.
“上帝不会掷骰子”
"God doesn't play dice."
一点也没错
Precisely.
你没想过要正式学习物理学？
You never thought of studying physics formally, Mr.Strauss?
我有过机会 但我选择卖鞋子
I had offers, but I chose to sell shoes.
路易斯·史劳斯曾是低微的鞋类销售员
Lewis Strauss was once a lowly shoe salesman.
不 就只是鞋类销售员
No, just a shoe salesman.
我可以介绍你们认识  -没必要
I'd love to introduce you. No need.
我认识他很多年了
I have known him for years.
阿尔伯特
Albert.
怎么回事？你跟他说了什么？
What was that? What did you say to him?
他没事啦
Oh, he's fine.
我的过去有些事你应该知道
Mr.Strauss, there are things in my past you ought to be aware of.
身为原子能委员会主席
Well, as chairman of the AEC,
我看过你的安全档案
I have access to your security file. I've read it.
你不担心？  -不担心
You're not worried? No.
你为国家贡献良多 我为什么要担心？
Why would I be worried after everything you've done for your country?
时代改变了 史特劳斯先生
Well, times change, Mr.Strauss.
这所研究院的目的…
Well, the purpose of this institute
就是为独立思想家提供避风港
is to provide a haven for independent minds.
你是这份工作的最佳人选
That's you. You are the man for the job.
我会考虑看看
Well, then I'll consider it.
明天在原子能委员会会议上见
I'll see you at the AEC meeting tomorrow.
这是全国威望最高的职位
This is one of the most prestigious appointments in the country.
是啊 而且通勤很方便
Yes, with a great commute.
所以我会考虑看看
That's why I'm considering it.
你在任命奥本海默博士之前他就提到…
So, Dr.Oppenheimer brought your attention to his past associations
他过去的左翼倾向？
before you appointed him?
是的
Yes.
你不感到担忧？
-And they didn't concern you?
我当时只担心他跟爱因斯坦
Just then I was entirely consumed with what he must have said to Einstein
说的话会让他讨厌我
to sour him on me.
但是后来呢？
But later?
我们都知道后来发生什么事
Well, we all know what happened later.
博士 你在欧洲…
Doctor, your time in Europe,
见过许多其他国家的物理学家
you seemed to meet with a wide range of other countries' physicists.
是的 没错
Yes, that's right.
有俄国人吗？
Any Russians?
一时想不到
None that spring to mind.
请让我继续宣读声明…
If you'll just allow me to continue with my statement--
罗博先生 你会有充分机会交叉诘问
Mr.Robb, you'll have ample opportunity to cross-examine.
我离开哥廷根后前往荷兰莱登大学
After Göttingen, I moved on to Leiden in Holland,
第一次见到伊西多拉比
where I first met Isidor Rabi.
不好意思
Excuse me.
美国佬讲解新物理学？我非听不可
A Yank, lecturing on the new physics? This I have to hear.
其实我也是美国人
I'm an American myself.
真没想到
How surprising.
需要帮你翻译英文就跟我说
Let me know if you need any help with the English.
等等 他在说什么？
Wait, what's he saying?
不了 谢谢
No, thank you.
到苏黎世还要很久
It's a long way to Zurich.
你再瘦一点就会陷入坐垫中间
You get any skinnier, we're gonna lose you between the seat cushions.
我是拉比
I'm Rabi.
我是奥本海默
Oppenheimer.
我听了你关于分子的讲课 只听懂一点
I caught your lecture on molecules. Caught some of it.
我们是纽约犹太人 你怎么会荷兰语？
We're a couple of New York Jews.How do you know Dutch?
我要来一个学期 最好学会荷兰语
Well, I thought I'd better learn it when I got here this semester.
你六周内就学会用荷兰语教量子力学？
You learned enough Dutch in six weeks to give a lecture on quantum mechanics?
我想挑战自己
Wanted to challenge myself.
量子物理学的挑战性还不够
Quantum physics wasn't challenging enough.
史威泽  -“史威泽”？
Schvitzer.Schvitzer?
爱现鬼
Show-off.
六周学会荷兰语却没学过意第绪语？
Dutch in six weeks, but you never learned Yiddish?
我住的高级住宅区不太会用到
They don't speak it so much my side of the park.
去你的
Screw you.
你想家吗？
You homesick?
当然了
-Oh, you know it.
我们这种人在这里好像不太受欢迎
Ever get the feeling our kind isn't entirely welcome here?
物理学家？
Physicists?
很搞笑  -在系上不会
That's funny. Not in the department.
他们也都是犹太人
They're all Jewish too.
吃吧
Eat.
你得去找一个德国人
There's a German you have to seek out.
海森堡  -没错
Heisenberg.Right.
人们可能会假设量子世界的背后…
One might be led to the presumption that behind the quantum world,
仍有一个因果关系成立的真实世界
there still hides a real world in which causality holds,
但这种假设对我们来说…
but such speculations seem to us,
老实说毫无用处 谢谢
to say it explicitly, fruitless. Thank you.
祝大家愉快
Have a great day.
太精彩了  -谢谢
Werner.Wonderful.Thank you.
奥本海默博士
Dr.Oppenheimer.
奥本海默 我喜欢你关于分子的论文
Oppenheimer, yes.I liked your paper on molecules.
那是受到你的启发
Probably because you inspired it.
我若还有什么启发 我们可以共同发表
If I inspire anything else, let me know. We could publish together.
我必须赶回美国
I have to get back to America.
为什么？那里没人认真看待量子力学
Why? There's no one there taking quantum mechanics seriously.
那就是原因
That's exactly why.
他很想念曼哈顿的峡谷
He's pining for the canyons of Manhattan.
新墨西哥州的峡谷
Canyons of New Mexico.
你来自新墨西哥州？
You're from New Mexico?
纽约 但我和弟弟在圣塔菲郊外有座牧场
No.New York, but my brother and I have a ranch outside Santa Fe.
那才是我想念的美国
That's the America I miss right now.
你们最好赶快回家 牛仔们
Then it's best you get home, cowboys.
只有他 我和马匹合不来
That's him. No, me and horses? I don't think so.
很高兴认识你
Nice to meet you.
你有没有再见到海森堡？
Did you ever encounter Heisenberg again?
没再见到本人 但…
Not in person, no, but, uh...
我们在工作上交过手
you might say our paths crossed.
我一回到美国就接受
On returning to America,
加州理工学院和伯克利的教职
I accepted positions at both Caltech and up at Berkeley.
放射实验室
我猜你就是劳伦斯博士
Dr.Lawrence, I presume?
你一定是奥本海默
You must be Oppenheimer.
是的
-Yes.
听说你想成立量子理论系所
I hear you want to start a school of quantum theory.
我已经在隔壁成立了
I am starting it.Next door.
你被安排在那里？
They put you in there?
是我要求的 我想接近你这种实验学者
I asked for it. Wanted to be close to you experimentalists.
理论是有局限的
Theory will get you only so far, huh?
我们在建造一台粒子加速器
We're building a machine to accelerate electrons.
太好了
Magnificent.
你想帮忙吗？
Would you like to help?
帮忙建造？不了
Build it? Oh, no.
但我想用它来测试我研究的理论
No, no. But I am working on theories I'd like to test with it.
你几时开始教课？
When do you start teaching?
第一堂课是一小时后
I've got my first in an hour.
小组讨论？
Seminar?
一名学生
-Pupil.
一名学生？就这样？
One student? That's it?
我要教没人梦想过的理论
I'm teaching something no one here has dreamt of.
但只要知道它能用来做什么…
But once people start hearing what you can do with it--
就无法回头
There's no going back.
我一定是走错…
Oh.I must have missed the--
洛马尼茨先生？
-Mr.Lomanitz?
对啊
Yeah.
就是这里 请进
Yes, this is it.Please.
坐下来
Take a seat.
你对量子力学了解多少？
What do you know about quantum mechanics?
我有一些基本的了解
I have a grasp on the basics.
那你就完全误解了
Then you're doing it wrong.
光是由粒子或波动构成？
Is light made up of particles or waves?
量子力学说两者都是 怎么可能？
Quantum mechanics says it's both.How could it be both?
不可能  -不可能
It can't.  -It can't.
但它是 这是悖论 但却成立
But it is. It's paradoxical, and yet, it works.
现在
Now...
谢谢
Thank you.
洛马尼茨先生 你不会被当掉
Mr.Lomanitz. You're gonna be okay.
史奈德先生
Mr.Snyder.
让我们想像一颗恒星
Now let's consider a star.
一个在外太空燃烧的巨大熔炉
A star. A vast furnace burning in outer space,
火焰违反自身重力向外扩散
fire pushing outwards against its own gravity.
达到平衡
Balanced.
当星体冷却 重力起作用 它就会收缩
But if that furnace cools and gravity starts winning, it contracts.
密度会增加
Density increases.
没错
Correct.
重力增加
Increasing gravity.
密度增加
Increasing density.  -And?
然后呢？  -这是恶性循环 直到…
It's a vicious cycle until...
极限是什么？
What's the limit here?
我也不知道
I don't know.
看数学带我们去哪里
See where the math takes us.
我保证是没有人去过的地方
I guarantee it's somewhere no one's been before.
你问我？
Me?
对 你的数学比我好
Yes, you.Your math is better than mine.
奥本海默的档案详记他在伯克利的活动
Dr.Oppenheimer's file contained details of his activities in Berkeley.
他们为何在战前就建立他的档案？
Why would they have started a file on Dr.Oppenheimer before the war?
这你就得去问胡佛先生
Well, you'd have to ask Mr.Hoover.
我在问你 史特劳斯少将
I'm asking you, Admiral Strauss.
我的假设是这跟他的…
Uh, my assumption is that it was connected to his,
左翼政治活动有关
uh, left-wing political activities.
周六下午两点西班牙忠诚派集会
你不该让学生在课堂上讨论政治 奥比
You shouldn't let them bring up politics in the classroom, Oppie.
那是我写的
I wrote that.
劳伦斯 你支持物理学革命
Lawrence, you embrace the revolution in physics.
难道看不出处处都有革命？
Can't you see it everywhere else?
毕卡索 史特拉汶斯基
Picasso, Stravinsky,
佛洛伊德 马克思
Freud, Marx.
这里是美国 奥比
Well, this is America, Oppie.
我们有过革命了
We had our revolution.
说真的 别带进实验室
Seriously, keep it out of the lab.
在实验室外 我房东今晚有场讨论会
Well, out of the lab, my landlady is having a discussion group tonight.
有兴趣吗？
Interested?
我参加过伯克利的政治活动
I have sampled the Berkeley political scene.
哲学系研究生和共产党员高谈种族共融
It's all just philosophy postgrads and communists talking integration.
你不关心种族共融
You don't care about integration?
我想投票支持 不是高谈阔论
I want to vote for it, not talk about it.
尤其是在周五 去吃饭吧
Especially on a Friday. Come on.Let's eat.
我要去见我弟弟
I'm meeting my brother there.
联邦调查局怎么会注意到这些活动？
And how would these activities have come to the attention of the FBI?
如果我没记错
Well, if I remember correctly,
联邦探员在共产党集会外面抄车牌时
the FBI was taking license plates outside suspected communist gatherings,
看到他的名字
and his name popped up.
吓到你了  -老天爷
Jesus Christ.
抱歉 哥  -弗兰克
Sorry. Frank.Robert.
你应该记得贾姬
Uh, you remember Jackie.
你好
Evening.
来吧
Let's go.
罗伯特 我要你见见薛瓦利埃
Robert. I want you to meet Chevalier.
哈肯薛瓦利埃博士
Dr.Haakon Chevalier,
罗伯特·奥本海默博士
Dr.Robert Oppenheimer.
幸会  -幸会 这是我弟弟弗兰克
Pleasure.Pleasure. This is my little brother, Frank.Hello.
这位是…
And this is--
还是贾姬
-Still Jackie.
你好 还是贾姬
Hello, Still Jackie.
薛瓦利埃 你在语言学系？
Chevalier, you're in languages?
我早就听说过你了
And your reputation precedes you.
你听说过我什么？
What have you heard?
你在教一门全新的物理学
That you're teaching a radical new approach to physics
我完全不懂 但我没听说你是党员
I have no chance of understanding, but I hadn't heard you're a Party member.
我不是  -还不是
I'm not.  -Not yet.
我和弗兰克正在考虑加入
Frank and I are thinking of joining.
我前几天…  -我支持各种行动
Just the other day, I was-- I support a range of causes.
西班牙内战？
The Spanish Civil War?
谁不支持法西斯暴徒推翻民主共和国
A democratic republic being overthrown by fascist thugs, who wouldn't?
美国政府
Our government.
他们认为社会主义比法西斯主义更危险
They think that socialism is a bigger threat than fascism.
很快就不会 看看纳粹怎么迫害犹太人
Not for long.Look at what the Nazis are doing to the Jews.
我寄钱给德国的同事让他们移民
I send funds to colleagues in Germany to emigrate.
我必须有点实际行动
I have to do something.
我的研究太抽象了
My own work is so abstract.
你在研究什么？
What are you working on?
恒星死亡后会发生什么事
What happens to stars when they die.
恒星会死亡？
Do stars die?
它们死亡后
Well, if they do,
会先冷却然后坍缩
they cool, then collapse.
恒星越大 过程会越猛烈
In fact, the bigger the star, the more violent its demise.
重力塌缩的强大力量会吞噬一切
Their gravity gets so concentrated, it swallows everything.
一切 包括光
Everything, even light.
那真的有可能发生？
Can that really happen?
数学说有可能
The math says it can.
若能发表论文 也许天文学家就会发现
If we can get published, then perhaps one day an astronomer finds one.
但目前只是理论 不会影响日常生活
But right now, all I have is theory, which can't impact people's lives.
你想寄钱去西班牙最好通过共产党
Well, if you're going to send money to Spain, do it through the Communist Party.
他们能把钱带到前线
They can get it to the front lines.
玛丽寄给我这些
-Mary sent me with these.
我是琼
I'm Jean.
我是罗伯特
Robert.
我是哈肯薛瓦利埃
Haakon Chevalier.
上个月在瑟伯尔家的工会会议？
The union meeting at Serber's last month.
对 没错
Right, right, yes.
谢谢
Oh, thank you.
罗伯特说他不是共产主义者
Robert here says he's not a communist.
那他就不够了解
Well, then he doesn't know enough about it.
我读完三卷《资本论》 这算不算？
I've read Das Kapital, all three volumes. Does that count?
你比大多数的党员读得更多
-It would make you better read than most party members.
太枯燥了 有些想法…
It's turgid stuff. There's some thinking,
“所有权就是窃盗”
"Ownership is theft."
“财产”
"Property."
“财产”？  -“财产” 不是“所有权”
"Property"? "Property," not "ownership."
抱歉 我读的是德文原版
I'm sorry, I read it in the original German.
失陪了
Well...
书不是重点
It's not about the book.
重点是想法 你似乎不太相信
It's about the ideas. And you sound uncommitted.
我相信应该自由思考如何改善世界
I'm committed to thinking freely about how to improve our world.
为何要局限于一种教条？
Why limit yourself to one dogma?
你是物理学家 你该挑选规则？
You're a physicist.You pick and choose rules?
或是该将你的精力投注于社会进步？
Or do you use the discipline to channel your energies into progress?
我喜欢有点转圜空间
I like a little wiggle room.
你总是坚守党的路线吗？
Do you always toe the party line?
我也喜欢有转圜空间
I like my wiggle room too.
怎么了？
What?
等等
Wait, wait, wait.
真没想到
Unexpected.
什么？
-What?
你看很多书嘛
For a physicist.
你的书架上只有佛洛伊德？
You only have a shelf full of Freud?
其实我比较倾向…
Well, actually, my background's more--
荣格？
Jungian?
你知道分析心理学？
You know analysis?
我在剑桥大学念研究所时出了点事
When I was a postgrad at Cambridge, I had a little trouble.
我洗耳恭听
I'll bite.
我试图毒死我的老师
I tried to poison my tutor.
你恨他吗？
Did you hate him?
我很喜欢他
I liked him very much.
你只是需要找人上床
You just needed to get laid.
我的心理师花了两年都没说到这重点
Took my analyst two years, and I don't think they ever put it that succinctly.
你让每个人都以为你这人很复杂
You have everyone convinced you're more complicated than you actually are.
每个人的本质都很单纯
We're all simple souls, I guess.
我就不是
I'm not.
这是什么？
What's this?
梵文
Sanskrit.
你能读梵文？
You can read this?
我正在学
I'm learning.
读这一段
Read this.
毗湿奴在这里显现他多臂的本相…
Well, in this part, Vishnu reveals his multi-armed self--
不是
No.
读出这一段话
Read the words.
“我现在成了死神”
"And now I am become Death."
“世界的毁灭者”
"The destroyer of worlds."
这里就行
This'll do.
暴风雨在日出前就会停息
It'll break before dawn.
晚上会降温 日出前就会停息
Air cools overnight.Just before dawn, it breaks.
来吧
Come on.Come on.
我要结婚了
I'm getting married.
弗兰克 恭喜了  -谢谢
Frank.Congratulations.  -Thank you.
是贾姬吗？
To Jackie?
对啊 是贾姬
Yeah, to Jackie.
那个女服务生
The waitress.
奥比 你说对了 暴风雨停息了
Oppie, you're right.It's lettin' up.
我要去看有没有星星
I'm gonna go see if there's any stars.
你老是说要支持平民百姓
All your talk about the common man,
却觉得贾姬不够好？
but Jackie's not good enough for you, hmm?
我们加入共产党
We join the Party,
你却无法掩饰你的不满
and you can't hide your disapproval, why?
那是因为你本来要加入吗？
Is that because that's supposed to be your thing?
我没有加入共产党
I haven't joined the Party, Frank.
我认为她不该说服你加入
And I don't think she should have convinced you to either.
有一半的教职员都是党员
Half of the faculty is communist.
我们系上不是
Not that half.
我是你哥 我要你小心点
I'm your brother, Frank, and I want you to be cautious.
我想扭断你脖子
And I want to wring your neck.
我不想过担心犯错的生活
I won't live my life afraid to make a mistake.
你很幸福 我替你高兴
You're happy, I'm happy.
我很高兴你为我感到高兴
So then I'm happy you're happy that I'm happy.
我好像能看到你在研究的暗星
I feel like I could see one of those dark stars that you're working on.
你不能 那就是重点
You can't.That's the whole point.
它们的重力吞噬了光
Their gravity swallows light.
就像太空中的一个洞
It's like a kind of hole in space.
弗兰克没事吧？
Is Frank okay?
没事 他只是有个烂哥哥
Yes.He just has a shitty brother.
这里很特别
It is special here.
我小时候…
When I was a kid,
以为只要想办法…
I thought if I could find a way
结合物理学和新墨西哥州
to combine physics and New Mexico,
我的人生就会圆满
my life would be perfect.
这里太偏僻了
Little remote for that.
是啊
Yes.
睡觉吧
Let's get some sleep.
今天看到的那片台地是我最喜欢的地方
That mesa we saw today, one of my favorite places in the world.
明天要爬上去
Tomorrow we'll climb it.
那地方叫什么？
What's it called?
洛斯阿拉莫斯
Los Alamos.
我没想到今天会见到你
I didn't expect to see you today.
我得先跟你预约吗？
Do I have to make an appointment?
嘿！给我回来！
Hey! Hey, get back here!
阿尔瓦雷茨？
-Alvarez?
奥比！奥比！
Oppie! Oppie!
干嘛？怎么了？
What? What is it?
他们做到了 德国的哈恩和施特拉斯曼
They've done it.They've done it. Hahn and Strassmann in Germany.
他们分裂了铀核
They split the uranium nucleus.
《旧金山纪事报》
原爆产生2亿伏特能量
怎么做到的？
How?
用中子撞击它
Bombarded it with neutrons.
那是核分裂
It's a nuclear fission.
他们造成原子核分裂
They did it, they split the atom.
那是不可能的
It's not possible.
我也要试着这么做
I'm gonna try to reproduce it.
瞧？不可能做到
See? Can't be done.
非常优雅 也很简单
Very elegant. Quite clear.
只有一个问题
There's just one problem.
在哪里？
Where?
隔壁
Next door.
阿尔瓦雷茨做到了
Alvarez did it.
看 这些核脉冲 非常巨大
But then look, these fission pulses, they're massive.
我在10分钟内看到30次
I've seen 30 of these in the past ten minutes.
理论是有局限的
Theory will take you only so far.
在这过程中…
During the process,
释放出的中子能用来分裂其它铀原子核
extra neutrons boil off, which could be used to split other uranium atoms.
造成连锁反应
Chain reaction.
你也在想同样的事
You're thinkin' what I'm thinkin'?
你我和全世界的物理学家都看到新闻
You, me and every other physicist around the world who's seen the news.
我们都在想什么事？
What? What are we all thinking?
一颗炸弹 阿尔瓦雷茨
A bomb, Alvarez.
一颗炸弹
A bomb.
我说过 别再送我花了
I told you, Robert, no more fucking flowers.
你要我做什么？
I don't understand what you want from me.
我什么都不要你做
I don't want anything from you.
但是你又打给我
Well, you say that and then you call.
那就不要回应
Well, don't answer.
我一定会回应
I'll always answer.
好吧
Fine.
但别再送花
Just no more flowers.
你不来吗？
You're not coming?
你要知道自己被拒绝 罗伯特
You have to know when you're beaten, Robert.
没那么简单 哈肯
It's not that simple, Hoke.
薛瓦利埃 很高兴见到你 芭芭拉…
Chevalier, good to see you.Barbara, good to see you,
还有著名的奥本海默博士
and the illustrious Dr.Oppenheimer.
我是艾尔坦顿
I'm Eltenton.
幸会了  -请吧
Pleasure. Please, please.
你能谈谈校园的组织化劳工吗？
Might you say a word about organized labor on campuses, yes?
借过！
Coming through! Coming through.
我在壳牌石油工作
I work at Shell.
化学家和工程师都加入
We've signed up chemists, we signed up engineers,
学术界的科学家为何不能？
so why not scientists in academia?
奥比…奥比…
Oppie! Oppie! Oppie! Oppie! Oppie! Oppie!
建筑师、工程师、化学家和技士
教师有工会 教授为何不能有？
Teachers are unionized. Why not professors?
你没别的事吗？
-Don't you have somewhere to be?
劳伦斯 学者也有权利
Lawrence, academics have rights too.
不是那样 我有个讨论小组
Look, it's not that.I've got a group coming.
那我要旁听
Oh.I'll sit in.
这次不行
Not this one.
理查德 布希博士
Richard.Dr.Bush.
你们怎么会来北加州？
What brings you two up north?
理查德 跟露丝说我周四会去帕萨迪纳
Richard, you tell Ruth I'll be down to Pasadena Thursday.
你的黑洞论文发表了！
Your paper on black holes is in!
哈特兰呢？把哈特兰找来
Where's Hartland? Get Hartland.Get Hartland.
1939年9月1日 世人会记得这一天
September 1st, 1939.The world's gonna remember this day.
哈特兰 我们的论文已经付梓了
Oh, Hartland.Our paper, it's in print.
你被抢了风头
We've been upstaged.
希特勒入侵波兰
“不是胜利就是死”  希特勒
在不列颠战役中 我越来越不同情…
During the Battle of Britain, I found myself increasingly out of sympathy
共产党提倡的中立政策
with the policy of neutrality that communists advocated.
希特勒入侵俄国后我们成为盟友
But after Hitler invaded Russia and we became allies,
你又开始同情共产党吗？
these communist sympathies, did they return?
没有
No.
我必须明确表示 我对俄国改变看法
I need to make clear that my changing views on Russia
并不代表我和意见相左的人士决裂
did not mean a sharp break from those who held different views.
在上一段婚姻有一两年…
For a year or two, and during a previous marriage,
我太太琪蒂曾经是共产党员
my wife Kitty had been a Communist Party member.
这里 我把好酒都放在这儿
This way.This is where I keep the good stuff.
我以为这是托尔曼家的房子
I thought this was the Tolmans' house.
我在加州理工学院时住过这里
I live with them while I'm at Caltech.
你们需要什么吗？
Do you two need anything?
不用了 露丝
-We're good, Ruthie.
所以 你是生物学家
So, you're a biologist.
但是现在却变成家庭主妇
Well, somehow I have graduated to housewife.
你能解释量子力学吗？真的很难懂
Can you explain quantum mechanics to me? Seems baffling.
没错
Yes, it is.
这个杯子
Well, this glass,
这杯酒
this drink,
这个台面
this countertop,
我们的身体
uh, our bodies,
所有的一切
all of it.
几乎都是虚体
It's mostly empty space.
许多微小能量波结合而成
Groupings of tiny energy waves bound together.
被什么结合？
By what?
强大的吸引力说服我们…
Forces of attraction strong enough to convince us
物质是固体
that matter is solid,
阻止我的身体穿过你的
stop my body passing through yours.
你嫁给哈里逊医师
You're married to Dr.Harrison.
我们很疏离
Not very.
我喜欢上一个女人…
There is someone that I feel--
她有同感吗？
Does she feel the same way?
有时候有 但是不够
Sometimes. Not enough.
我要去新墨西哥州
You know, I'm going to New Mexico.
带朋友去我的牧场
To my ranch, with friends.
你应该一起来
You should come.
我是说带着你先生
I meant with your husband.
才怪
Yes, you did.
你根本就不在乎他去不去
'Cause you know it won't make a bit of difference.
你为什么嫁给他？
Why did you marry him?
我当时很迷惘 他人很好
I was lost and he was kind.
迷惘？
Lost?
我的前夫死了 而且…
Well, my previous husband had died,
我才28岁 不想当个寡妇
and at 28 I wasn't really ready to be a widow.
你第一任丈夫是谁？
Who was your first husband?
谁都不是 但我第二任丈夫是乔戴勒
Nobody.But my second husband was Joe Dallet.
他跟我一样出身富裕家庭 但…
He was, um, from money, like me,
他在俄亥俄州扬斯敦组织工会 我很爱他
but he was a union organizer in Youngstown, Ohio. Fell hard.
多爱他？
How hard?
接下来四年只吃豆子和煎饼
Hard enough to spend the next four years living off beans and pancakes,
在工厂大门散发《工人日报》
handing out the Daily Worker at factory gates.
到了36岁我跟乔说我再也受不了
By 36, I just told Joe I couldn't take it anymore.
但退党后一年又想要他回来
Quit the Party.A year later, I wanted him back.
他 不是《工人日报》…
Him, not the Daily Worker.
他说 “太好了 我们在西班牙见”
He said, "Swell, I'll meet you on my way to Spain."
他去为忠诚派打仗？
He went to fight for the Loyalists?
他加入国际旅 我只好耐心等
And then he went to the brigades and I waited,
然后…
and...
乔一从战壕探出头来就被射死
Joe got himself killed first time he popped his head outta the trench.
意识形态害乔白白牺牲
Ideology got Joe killed.For nothing.
他是为西班牙共和国牺牲
Spanish Republic isn't nothing.
我丈夫付出我们的未来
My husband offered both our futures to stop one fascist bullet
却只阻止了一颗法西斯子弹
from embedding itself in a mudbank.
那绝对是白白牺牲
That's the definition of nothing.
那未免太消极了
Seems a little reductive.
我只是务实
Pragmatic.
我来到这里
Now here I am.
不知道这算什么
Wherever the hell this is.
我不希望你从别人口中得知
I didn't want you to hear it from anyone else.
至少你这次没送我花
Least you didn't bring me flowers.
我们都知道我不是你要的
We both know I'm not what you want, Jean.
是啊 但我们不会再见面了
Yeah, but it's a door closing.
不
No.
对我来说不是这样
Not as far as I'm concerned, no.
你把她的肚子搞大 有够快
You knocked her up.Fast work.
我是个厉害角色
Can't keep a good man down.
她才是
I meant her.
她很清楚自己要什么
She knew what she wanted.
她丈夫呢？
What about the husband?
我们谈过了…
We talked.
他们会离婚
They're getting a divorce
我们可以趁她肚子隆起前结婚
so we can get married before she starts showing.
想得真周到
How civilized.
你这个傻瓜
You idiot.
这是你的圈子
This is your community.
你以为你这金童不必守规矩？
You think the rules don't apply to the golden boy?
我有非凡成就就够了
Brilliance makes up for a lot.
别得罪这世上唯一了解你研究的人
Don't alienate the only people in the world that understand what you do.
有一天你会需要他们
One day you might need them.
建筑师、工程师、化学家、技工联盟
The Federation of Architects, Engineers, Chemists and Technicians.
放射实验室工会化
建筑师工程师化学家技工联盟
洛马尼茨 你的月薪多少？
Lomanitz, what do you get paid a month?
那不是重点 劳伦斯
-That's not the point, Lawrence.
你们跟农工和码头工人有何共通点？
What do any of you have in common with farm laborers and dock workers?
很多共通点
Plenty.
大家都出去 马上！
Everybody out.Now!
你留下来
Not you.
你在做什么？
What are you doing?
这是个工会
It's a trade union.
全都是共产党员
Filled with communists.
我又没入党
So? I haven't joined the Party.
他们会因为这种事不让你加入计划
They won't let me bring you onto the project because of this shit.
这是什么计划都不会告诉你
They won't even let me tell you what the project is.
我知道这是什么计划
Oh, I know what the project is.
真的吗？
Oh, really?
爱因斯坦和西拉德寄信给罗斯福
We've all heard about Einstein and Szilard's letter to Roosevelt
警告他德国人能制造原子弹
warning him the Germans could make a bomb,
我知道纳粹有一颗原子弹代表什么
and I know what it means for the Nazis to have a bomb.
我就不知道？
And I don't?
他们送进集中营的不是你的同胞
It's not your people they're herding into camps.
是我的同胞
It's mine.
你以为我跟他们说你的政治立场
You think that I tell them about your politics.
下次你开完会回家
The next time you're coming home from a meeting,
何不看看你的照后镜？
why don't you take a look in the rearview mirror?
听听电话线的声音 别这么天真
Listen to the sounds on your phone line and stop being so goddamn naive.
他们为何在乎我做什么？
Why would they care what I do?
你不是自以为很重要 是真的很重要
Because you're not just self-important, you're actually important.
好
Okay.
好 我懂了
I get it.
如果你可以再…
If you could just be a little more--
务实一点
Pragmatic.
我会跟洛马尼茨和其他人说…
I'll talk to Lomanitz, I'll talk to the others.
你不必担心 不会有事
You don't have to worry.It's done,
劳伦斯
Lawrence.
那就欢迎加入战争
Then welcome to the war.
我填完安全调查问卷后被告知
I filled out my first security questionnaire
我和左翼团体的关系不会是…
and was informed that my involvement with left-wing groups
参与原子能计划的障碍
would not prove a bar to my working on the atomic program.
他亲共的立场
Why were his communist associations
在战时为何不构成国安风险？
not seen as a security risk during the war?
参议员 我不可能知道…
Senator, I can't possibly answer for security clearance
我们认识前他为何获得安全许可
granted years before I ever met the man.
好吧 之后呢？
Fine.What about after?
奥本海默博士在战后
After the war,
成为全世界最受尊敬的科学家
Dr.Oppenheimer was the most respected scientific voice in the world.
我才会请他担任院长
That's why I asked him to run the Institute.
并且担任原子能委员会的顾问
That's why he advised the Atomic Energy Commission.
就这么简单
Simple as that.
他们在指控我什么？
What are they accusing me of?
1947年到1954年发生了什么事
I think they just wanna know what happened between 1947 and 1954
改变你对于给予他安全许可的看法
to change your mind on Oppenheimer's security clearance.
并没有 我当时是原子能委员会主席
I didn't. I was chair of the AEC,
但我没对罗伯特提出指控
but it wasn't me that brought the charges against Robert.
是谁提出的？
Who did?
国会联席委员会的前任职员
Some former staff member of the Joint Congressional Committee.
一个叫波登的狂热反共分子
He was a rabid anti-communist named Borden.
他写信要求联邦调查局采取行动
He wrote to the FBI demanding they take action.
何不直接找原子能委员会？
The FBI? Why not go to the AEC direct?
他想要借刀杀人
Why get caught holding the knife yourself?
波登跟奥本海默有什么仇？
What did Borden have against Oppenheimer?
那是麦卡锡时代
This was the McCarthy Era.
只要跟共产党沾上边就会丢掉饭碗
People hounded out of jobs for any hint of red.
他又看过奥本海默的安全档案
And then, reading Oppenheimer's security file,
知道他弟弟、弟媳、未婚妻
his communist brother, sister-in-law, fiancée,
好友和妻子都是共产党员
best friend, wife.
那还是在薛瓦利埃事件之前
That's before we even get to the Chevalier incident.
波登怎么会有奥本海默的安全档案？
But how would Borden have access to Oppenheimer's security file?
联邦调查局
因为有人交给他
Because somebody gave it to him.
有人想让罗伯特噤声
Somebody who wanted Robert silenced.
谁？  -谁知道？
Who? Who knows?
罗伯特得罪了很多华府权贵
Robert didn't take care not to upset the power brokers in Washington.
他对原子能的意见成为主流
His opinions on the atom became definitive
对我们这些凡夫俗子也没有耐心
and he wasn't always patient with us mere mortals.
我接任后受到严厉的批评
I came in for plenty of harsh treatment.
有一次原子能委员会投票表决
There was an AEC vote
是否该向挪威出口同位素
on the export of isotopes to Norway,
他们把罗伯特找来让我出糗
and they drafted in Robert to make me look like a fool.
奥本海默博士 史特劳斯少将表示…
But, Dr.Oppenheimer, we've already heard from Admiral Strauss
这些同位素可能用来帮助敌人制造核武
that these isotopes could be useful to our enemies in the production of atomic weapons.
各位 铁铲能用来制造核武 是真的
Congressmen, you could use a shovel in making atomic weapons. In fact, you do.
一瓶啤酒都能用来制造核武 也是真的
You could use a bottle of beer in making atomic weapons. In fact, you do.
同位素不像电子零件那么有用
I say isotopes are less useful than electronic components,
但是比三明治更有用
but more useful than a sandwich.
天才不一定是智者
Genius is no guarantee of wisdom.
这个人曾经历许多怎会如此盲目？
How could this man who saw so much be so blind?
琪蒂？
Kitty?
琪蒂…
Kitty,
那项计划 我加入了
the project-- I'm in.
我加入了
I'm in.
让我们庆祝吧
Let's celebrate.
你不去哄他吗？
Shouldn't you go to him?
我已经哄了他一整天
I have been going to him all fucking day.
让我来抱
Come here, darling.
我不知道该如何启齿
I don't know how to say this.
我惭愧到不敢说
I-I'm ashamed to ask.
尽管说
Anything.
请你们照顾彼得
Take Peter.
没问题-只是暂时的
-Sure. No, for a while, Hoke.
暂时的
A while.
琪蒂知道你来这里吗？
Does Kitty know you're here?
她当然知道
Yes, of course she knows.
Of course she knows.
我们很可恶 又自私又可恶
We're awful people.Selfish, awful people.
忘了我的要求
Forget I asked.
又自私又可恶的人
Selfish, awful people,
不会知道自己又自私又可恶
they don't know they're selfish and awful.
坐下来
Sit, sit, sit.
罗伯特 你看到超越这世界的奥秘
Robert, you see beyond the world we live in.
必须为此付出代价
There is a price to be paid for that.
我们当然会帮助你
Of course we'll help you.
一切都在改变 罗伯特
Everything's changing, Robert.
有了小孩一定会改变…
Having a child was always going to change--
世界正在改变 转向一个全新方向
No, the world, it's pivoting in some new direction.
重组新秩序
It's reforming.
这是属于你的时刻
This is your moment.
我们成立一个小组研究…
We're putting together a group to study feasibili--
别找其他人 你要靠自己
"We" shouldn't be doing anything.You should.
劳伦斯成不了大事
Lawrence won't get this done.
托尔曼或拉比也不行 只有你行
Or Tolman, or Rabi.You will.
穿军服的是什么人？
Who are the uniforms?
我以为你知道
I thought you might know.
奥本海默博士
Dr.Oppenheimer.
我是格罗夫斯上校 这是尼柯斯中校
I'm Colonel Groves. This is Lieutenant Colonel Nichols.
拿去干洗
Have that dry cleaned.
你是这么对待一名中校
Well, if that's how you treat Lieutenant Colonel,
谁知道你会怎么对待谦卑的物理学家
I'd hate to see how you treat a humble physicist.
我没见过谦卑的物理学家
If I ever meet one, I'll let you know.
好狠啊  -世界各地都有战事
Ouch. Theaters of combat all over the world,
我却必须留在华府  -为什么？
but I have to stay in Washington. Why?
我负责建造五角大厦
-I built the Pentagon.
高层很满意 要我接管曼哈顿工程区
The brass likes it so much they made me take over the Manhattan Engineer District.
那是什么？
Which is?
别装蒜 你知道那是什么
Don't be a smart ass. You know damn well what it is.
你和全国一半的物理系都知道
You and half of every physics department across the country.
那是第一个问题
That's problem number one.
我以为第一个问题是取得足够的铀矿
I thought problem number one would be securing enough uranium ore.
我上任那天就买了1千2百吨
1,200 tons bought the day I took charge.
运到提炼厂了？
-Processing?
已经在田纳西州橡树岭破土动工
Just broke ground at Oak Ridge, Tennessee.
我在找这项计划的负责人
Now I'm looking for a project director.
有人提起我的名字？
And my name came up?
没有
Nope.
虽然你把量子物理学引进美国
Even though you brought quantum physics to America.
这让我很好奇
Which made me curious.
你发现了什么？
-What've you found out?
你吊儿郎当、风流成性
You're a dilettante, a womanizer,
可能是共产党员
a suspected communist--
我是新政民主党员
I'm a New Deal Democrat.
我说可能是
I said "suspected."
不安于室、浮夸爱现
Unstable, theatrical,
狂妄自大、神经兮兮…
egotistical, neurotic--
没有好话？“他很杰出 但…”
Nothing good, no? Not even, "He's brilliant, but--"
这圈子每个人都很杰出 没好话
Well, brilliance is taken for granted in your circle, so no.
唯一说过你好话的是理查德托尔曼
No, the only person who had anything good to say was Richard Tolman.
托尔曼认为你很有原则
Tolman thinks you have integrity,
但我看他比较了解科学却不会看人
but he also strikes me as a guy who knows more about science than people.
你不相信任何人却还是来找我
Yet here you are. You don't take much on trust.
我不相信任何事情
I don't take anything on trust.
你为什么没得到诺贝尔奖？
Why don't you have a Nobel prize?
你为什么不是将军？
Why aren't you a general?
这件事会让我当上将军
-They're making me one for this.
也许我也会一样幸运
Perhaps I'll have the same luck.
因为发明原子弹得到诺贝尔奖？
A Nobel prize for making a bomb?
诺贝尔发明了炸药
Alfred Nobel invented dynamite.
你会怎么进行？
So how would you proceed?
你说的是利用理论
You're talking about turning theory
制造一个实用的武器系统
into a practical weapons system
还要抢先纳粹一步
faster than the Nazis.
他们领先我们整整12个月
Who have a 12-month head start.
18个月-你怎么可能知道？
Eighteen.  -How could you possibly know that?
我们的快中子研究耗时6个月
Our fast neutron research took six months.
他们任命的负责人会立刻成功做到
The man they've undoubtedly put in charge will have made that leap instantly.
他们的负责人会是谁？
Who do you think they put in charge?
维尔纳海森堡
-Werner Heisenberg.
他对原子结构的理解无人能及
He has the most intuitive understanding of atomic structure I have ever seen.
你了解他的研究？
You know his work?
他、瓦尔特博特、冯魏茨泽克、第伯纳
-I know him. Just like I know Walther Bothe, Von Weizsäcker, Diebner.
这场比赛德国人赢定了
In a straight race, the Germans win.
我们只有一个希望
We've got one hope.
是什么？
Which is?
反犹太主义
Anti-Semitism.
什么？
What?
希特勒称量子物理学为“犹太科学”
Hitler called quantum physics "Jewish science."
当着爱因斯坦的面说
Said it right to Einstein's face.
唯一的希望是希特勒被仇恨蒙蔽
Our one hope is that Hitler is so, so blinded by hate
剥夺海森堡的资源 这需要大量资源
that he's denied Heisenberg proper resources, because it'll take vast resources.
全国最优秀的科学家共同努力
Our nation's best scientists, working together.
现在他们分散各地
Right now, they're scattered.
这样才能划分权限
Which gives us compartmentalization.
所有人都得看到全局才能有效工作
All minds have to see the whole task to contribute efficiently.
安全漏洞也许会害我们输掉比赛
Poor security may cost us the race.
效率低落绝对会输
Inefficiency will.
反正德国人知道的比我们多
The Germans know more than us anyway.
俄国人没有
The Russians don't.
提醒我 我们在和谁作战？
Remind me, who are we at war with?
你曾有左倾的立场 最好别落人口舌
Somebody with your past doesn't wanna be seen downplaying
说你低估防范共产党盟友的重要性
the importance of security from our communist allies.
我了解 但不要
Point taken.But, no.
你不能对我说“不”
You don't get to say "no" to me.
你错了 我的职责就是对你说“不”
It's my job to say "no" to you when you're wrong.
你想要这份工作？
So you have the job now?
我正在考虑
Uh, I'm considering it.
我终于知道你有多难搞了
I'm starting to see where you got your reputation.
我最喜欢的说法是
My favorite response?
“奥本海默连小吃摊都管不好”
"Oppenheimer couldn't run a hamburger stand."
我是管不好
I couldn't.
但我能掌管曼哈顿计划
But I can run the Manhattan Project.
有办法平均分配工作
There's a way to balance these things.
劳伦斯负责伯克利的放射实验室
Keep the Rad Lab here at Berkeley under Lawrence.
西拉德负责芝加哥的冶金实验室
Met Lab in Chicago under Szilard.
在哪里大量提炼铀矿？田纳西州
Large scale refining, where did you say? Tennessee.
还有汉福德  -汉福德
And Hanford.And Hanford.
美国所有的工业实力和科学创新
All America's industrial might and scientific innovation,
全都通过铁路连结
connected by rail.
专注于一个目标
Focused on one goal.
各地同时进行的研究汇聚在这里
One point in space and time.And it comes together here.
一间位置偏僻的秘密实验室
A secret laboratory. In the middle of nowhere,
既安全又自给自足…
secure, self-sufficient,
设备和住宿全都有
equipment, housing, the works.
谁都不能离开 直到完成为止
Keep everyone there until it's done.
我会需要学校、商店和教堂
I'll need the schools, stores, a church.
为什么？
-Why?
不让科学家携家带眷
If we don't let scientists bring their families,
就找不到最优秀的人才
we'll never get the best.
想要保密就必须尽快建造一个城镇
You want security, build a town, build it fast.
在哪里？
Where?
欢迎来到洛斯阿拉莫斯
Welcome to Los Alamos.
我们必须征用一所男校
Now, there's a boys' school we'll have to commandeer
这也是印第安人的墓地
and the local Indians come up here for burial rites.
除此之外 方圆64公里什么都没有
But, apart from that, nothing. Forty miles.Any direction.
可以找到完美的地点
Enough to find the perfect spot.
用来做什么？
What for?
缔造成功
-Success.
尽快建造一个城镇
Build him a town.Fast.
我们去招募科学家吧
Let's go recruit some scientists.
我为什么要离开家人？
Why would I leave my family?
我说过你能携家带眷
I told you, you can bring your family.
我不是士兵 奥比
I'm not a soldier, Oppie.
士兵？他是少将 我不缺士兵
A soldier? He's a general. I've got all the soldier I need.
我能告诉他们什么？
What can I tell them?
海森堡、第伯纳、博特和波耳
Heisenberg, Diebner, Bothe, Bohr.
他们有什么共通点？
What do these men have in common?
原子理论最伟大的科学家
The greatest minds on atomic theory.
对 还有呢？
Yes, and? Uh...
你要多少都有
As much as you like,
再啰嗦我就痛扁你
until you feel my boot on your balls.
你们比任何人都更了解同位素和炸药
You know isotopes and you know explosives, better than anyone in the world.
但你不能说你在做什么？
But you can't tell us what you're doing.
我不知道  -他们为纳粹工作
I don't know.The Nazis have them.
波耳在哥本哈根  -已被纳粹占领
Niels Bohr's in Copenhagen.Under Nazi occupation.
普林斯顿没有报纸吗？
Did they stop printing newspapers in Princeton?
为什么要去鸟不生蛋的地方
Why would we go to the middle of nowhere
谁知道要待多长的时间？
for who knows how long?
一两年 或是三年
A year or two.Or three.
少将 请你离开一下
General, could you give us a moment?
我们要抢先纳粹一步释放一股巨大力量
It's about unleashing the strong force before the Nazis do.
天啊
Oh, my God.
波耳不会为纳粹工作  -绝对不会
Niels won't work for the Nazis.No, never.
但他在纳粹手上 所以我需要你
But while they have him, we don't. That's why I need you.
你为什么认为我会答应？
Why would you think I'd do that?
为什么？为什么？
Why? Why?
因为这将是人类史上
How about because this is the most important fucking thing
最重要的发明
to ever happen in the history of the world.
怎么样？
How about that?
该死
Fuck.
他们不会让我加入计划
They are not gonna let me onto this project.
没通过安全查核在战后会毁了我的职涯
And failing a security check is not gonna be good for a career, even after the war.
你是共产党同路人 又怎样？
So you're a fellow traveler.
现在是国家紧急状态
So what? This is a national emergency.
我也有秘密 但他们让我负责
I've got some skeletons, they put me in charge.
他们需要我们
They need us.
直到他们不需要
Until they don't.
能不能把波耳弄出丹麦？
Is there any chance of getting Bohr out of Denmark?
不能 我问过英国人
Nah, no dice. I checked with the British.
盟军展开反攻之前
Until we get Allied boots back onto the continent,
一点办法都没有
there's just no way.
他有那么重要？
Is he that important?
有多少人证明过爱因斯坦是错的？
How many people do you know who've proved Einstein wrong?
坐飞机真的会比较快
You know, it really would be quicker to take a plane.
不行 太危险了
No, plane's too risky.
国家需要我们
Country needs us.
哈佛的家伙说建筑物装不下回旋加速器
The Harvard guys, they say the building's too small for the cyclotron.
让他们和建筑师开会
Get them together with the architects.
这地方几时开始运作？
When's this place supposed to open?
两个月后
Two months.
你很会临机应变 但这件事…
Robert, you're the great improviser, but this...
光靠你自己的头脑做不到
you can't do in your head.
四组
Four divisions.
实验、理论、冶金、军械
Experimental, Theoretical, Metallurgical, Ordnance.
谁负责理论组？
Who's running Theoretical?
我
I am.
我就怕会是这样
That's what I was afraid of.
你分身乏术
You're spread too thin.
你负责理论组
So you take Theoretical.
我不会来这里 罗伯特
I'm not coming here, Robert.
为什么？
Why not?
你投放的炸弹会炸死好人和坏人
You drop a bomb, and it falls on the just and the unjust.
我不希望累积三世纪的物理学…
I don't wish the culmination of three centuries of physics
成为大规模毁灭性武器
to be a weapon of mass destruction.
伊西
Izzy.
我不知道人类能否被信任使用这种武器
I don't know if we can be trusted with such a weapon.
但我知道纳粹不能使用
But I know the Nazis can't.
我们别无选择
We have no choice.
那么…
Then...
你要做的第二件事就是
the second thing you'll have to do is appoint Hans Bethe
任命汉斯贝特负责理论组
to run the theoretical division.
等等 第一件事是什么？
Wait, what was the first?
脱掉那套可笑的军服
Take off that ridiculous uniform.
你是科学家
You're a scientist.
格罗夫斯坚持要我们从军
Groves is insisting we join.
叫格罗夫斯去吃屎吧
Tell Groves to go shit in his hat.
他们需要我们 做自己吧
They need us for who we are.
做更好的自己
So be yourself.Only better.
这是唯一的钥匙
This is the only key.
泰勒已经来了
And Teller's already here.
要让他进来吗？
Shall I just show him in?
不 先等其他人
No, let's wait for the others.
我们开始吧
Let's get started.
你好 爱德华
Hello, Edward.
你好
Yes.
我们先在这里工作 直到T组完工
Gentlemen, so, we will work here until the T-section at Los Alamos is finished.
爱德华 请你
Edward, can I please--
这比较重要
It is more important.
我在计算连锁反应时
When I calculated the chain reaction,
发现一个令人不安的可能性
I found a rather troubling possibility.
不是吧
No.
这不可能是对的
This can't be right.
让我看你是怎么算出来的
Show me how you did your calculations.
好的
Yes.
这是指数函数  -不对
It's exponential.No.No, no, no.No.
这是幻想
This is fantasy.
泰勒的计算不可能是对的
Teller's calculations can't be right.
你再计算一次 我要去普林斯顿
Do them yourself while I go to Princeton.
为什么？  -跟爱因斯坦谈谈
What for? To talk to Einstein.
你们俩意见完全不同
There's not much common ground between you two.
所以才要征求他的意见
That's why I should get his view.
阿尔伯特
Albert.  -Mmm?
奥本海默博士
Ah, Dr.Oppenheimer.
你见过哥德尔博士吗？
Well, have you met Dr.Gödel?
我们都在这里散步
We walk here most days.
树木是最启发人心的结构
Trees are the most inspiring structures.
阿尔伯特 能聊聊吗？
Albert, might I have a word?
当然 失陪了 库尔特
Of course.Excuse me, Kurt.
有些日子库尔特拒绝进食
You know, some days, Kurt refuses to eat.
就连在普林斯顿也一样
Even in Princeton.
他认为纳粹能在他的食物中下毒
He's convinced that the Nazis can poison his food.
这是谁算出来的？
Whose--Whose work is this?
泰勒
Teller's.
你认为这代表什么？
What do you take it to mean?
中子撞击原子核
Neutrons smash into nucleus,
释放中子撞击其它原子核
releasing neutrons to smash into other nuclei.
到达临界点就会产生巨大爆炸
Criticality, a point of no return, massive explosive force.
但这时候连锁反应不会停止
But this time, the chain reaction doesn't stop.
而是会点燃大气层
It would ignite the atmosphere.
当我们引爆原子弹
When we detonate an atomic device,
可能会引发连锁反应
we might start a chain reaction that...
毁灭全世界
destroys the world.
到了这个地步？
So here we are, hmm?
迷失在你的量子机率世界中…
Lost in your quantum world of probabilities
需要一个确定性
and needing certainty.
你能亲自计算吗？
Can you run the calculations yourself?
你我唯一的共通点就是厌恶数学
About the only thing you and I have in common is a disdain for mathematics.
谁在伯克利研究这个？
Who's working on this in Berkeley?
汉斯·贝特
Hans Bethe.
他会查出真相
Well, he'll get to the truth.
如果是毁天灭地的真相呢？
And if the truth is catastrophic?
那你就停下来
Then you stop.
把你的发现和纳粹分享
And you share your findings with the Nazis.
确保任何一方都不会毁灭世界
So neither side destroys the world.
罗伯特
Robert.
这是你的责任 不是我的
This is yours, not mine.
泰勒错了 他错了
Teller's wrong. He's wrong.Shh, shh, shh...
当你了解泰勒的假设 就知道真实状况
When you know Teller's critical assumptions, the real picture emerges.
结果是什么？
Bottom line?
核反应失控的机率几乎是零
The chances of an uncontrolled nuclear reaction are near zero.
几乎是零
Near zero.
奥比 这是好消息
Oppie, this is good news.
再算一次
Can you run them again?
你会得到同样的答案
No, you'll get the same answer.
真的引爆这玩意之前…
Till they actually detonate one of these things,
这是最好的保证
the best assurance you're going to get is this.
几乎是零
Near zero.
理论是有局限的
Theory will take you only so far.Mmm.
你们好
Hello!
你好  -嗨
-Hello, you.
我们好想他
We missed him.
想领养吗？  -她在开玩笑
You want to adopt? She's kidding.
我们走之前想见你
We wanted to see you before we left.
前往未知领域
For parts unknown.
知道我前几天遇到谁吗？
You know who I ran into the other day?
艾尔坦顿
Eltenton.
壳牌石油的化学家？工会的家伙？
The chemist from Shell? The union guy?
对 工会的家伙
Yeah.The FAECT guy.
他在抱怨美国处理战争的方法
He was moaning about how we're handling the war.
怎么说？
How so?
缺乏和盟友的合作
Lack of cooperation with our allies.
政府没和俄国人分享任何研究成果
Apparently our government's not sharing any research with the Russians.
他说多数的科学家都觉得这政策很蠢
Well, he said, "Most scientists think the policy is stupid."
是吗？  -是啊
Oh, yeah? Yeah.
他提到有人若想绕过官方管道…
He mentioned that if anyone had anything they wanted to pass on,
传递任何情报 他都能帮忙
going around official channels, that he could help.
那是叛国罪
That would be treason.
当然了
Yes, of course.
我只想让你知道
I just thought you should know.
小淘气睡着了
The brat is down.
马丁尼呢？
Where are the martinis?
马上来
Coming right up.
我们只聊到那里
The conversation ended there.
我们是老朋友 我不相信
Nothing in our long-standing friendship would have led me to believe
薛瓦利埃真的在搜集情报
that Chevalier was actually seeking information,
我也很确定他不知道我在做什么
and I am certain that he had no idea of the work in which I was engaged.
我很早就知道应该立刻报告这件事
It has long been clear to me that I should have reported this incident at once.
奥本海默事件凸显了科学家
The Oppenheimer situation highlights the tension
和国家安全机关之间的冲突
between scientists and the security apparatus.
为了得知候选人
In hopes of learning how the nominee handled such issues
在AEC任职时如何处理这问题
during his time at the AEC,
我们将请一位科学家出席作证
we'll have a scientist appearing before the committee.
他们要找谁来？
Who are they bringing in?
他们没说
They haven't said.
主席先生 我被提名为商务部部长
Mr.Chairman, if I may, I'm nominated for commerce secretary.
为何要征求科学家的意见？
Why seek the opinion of scientists?
这是内阁职位 少将
This is a cabinet post, Admiral.
我们会征求各方意见
We seek a wide range of opinion.
我想知道出席作证的科学家是谁
Well, I'd like to know the name of the scientist testifying,
也想进行交叉诘问
I'd like the chance to cross-examine.
这不是法庭
This is not a court.
只是走程序？
Formality, huh?
1925年后没有内阁候选人
No presidential Cabinet nominee
未能得到确认任命
has failed to be confirmed since 1925.
这只是游戏规则
This is just how the game is played.
十拿九稳 路易斯
It's in the bag, Lewis.
好好配合就行
So play nice.
他们请来科学家又怎样？
They bring in a scientist, so what?
你不像我那么了解科学家
You don't know scientists like I do, Counselor.
他们讨厌质疑他们判断的任何人
They resent anyone who questions their judgment,
尤其是局外人
especially if you're not one of them.
我曾是原子能委员会主席
I was chair of the AEC.
罗伯特的事会怪在我身上
I'm easy to blame for what happened to Robert.
我们不能让参议院觉得…
We can't have the Senate thinking the scientific community
科学界不支持你 先生
doesn't support you, sir.
也许应该改变说词？
Or should we pivot?  -To what?
怎么改变？  -采取强硬立场
And embrace it.
我杠上奥本海默 美国赢了
"I fought Oppenheimer and the US won."
我觉得不该这么说
I-I don't think we need to go there.
谁知道到底发生什么事？
Isn't there someone we can call who knows what really happened?
泰勒
Teller.
他的份量够重
-He'll make an impression.
你能查出那个科学家是谁吗？
Can you get the name of the scientist they've called?  -Probably.
大概吧  -查出他在战时是在…
Find out if he was based in Chicago
芝加哥或是洛斯阿拉莫斯
or Los Alamos during the war.
那有何关系？
Why does that matter?
他在芝加哥就是替西拉德和费米工作
-If he was based in Chicago, he worked under Szilard and Fermi,
不是替奥比创立的邪教工作
not the cult of Oppie at Los Alamos.
罗伯特一手建造那地方
Robert built that damn place.
他是创始者、市长、警长
He was founder, mayor, sheriff,
简直就是一个神
all rolled into one.
洛斯阿拉莫斯计划
大门
这里只缺一间酒馆
All it needs is a saloon. Let's go and see.
没有厨房
There's no kitchen.
是吗？我们会解决
Really? We'll fix that.
铁丝网围栏、枪械
Barbed wire? Guns?
奥比
Oppie.
我们在打仗 汉斯
We're at war, Hans.
哈利法克斯 1917年
Halifax, 1917.
一艘满载炸药的货船在港口爆炸
A cargo ship carrying munitions explodes in the harbor.
引发巨大和突然的化学反应
A vast and sudden chemical reaction.
历史上最大的人为爆炸
The biggest man-made explosion in history.
如果是核反应而非化学反应
Now let's calculate how much more destructive it would have been
计算破坏会有多大
if it were a nuclear, and not a chemical, reaction.
以黄色炸药的吨数表示威力
Expressing power in terms of tons of TNT.
那会是上千吨威力
But it will be thousands.
那就以千吨计算
Well, then...kilotons.
使用铀-235
Using U-235,
原子弹会需要…
the bomb will need--Ah...
抱歉 小工具会需要这大小的15公斤圆球
Right, sorry. Gadget will need a 33-pound sphere about this size.
使用钚则需要4.5公斤圆球
Or using plutonium, the ten-pound sphere.
这是橡树岭上个月提炼的铀量
Here's the amount of uranium Oak Ridge refined all of last month.
这是汉福德工厂生产的钚
And the Hanford plant made this much plutonium.
如果能浓缩这些 就必须设法引爆
Now, if we can enrich these amounts, we need a way to detonate them.
爱德华 你觉得无聊吗？
Are we boring you, Edward?
有一点
A little bit, yes.
请问为什么？
May I ask why?
我们都知道有可能制造原子弹
We all entered this room knowing a fission bomb was possible.
不如用点新玩意
How about we leave it with something new?
像是什么？
-Such as?
用氢取代铀或是钚
Instead of uranium or plutonium, we use hydrogen.
重氢  -氢
Heavy hydrogen.
氘 懂吗？
Deuterium. You see?
用巨大压力把原子核…
We compact the atoms together under great pressure
压缩在一起 引发融合反应
to induce a fusion reaction.
爆炸威力不只是数千吨
Then we'll get not kilotons,
而是数百万吨
but megatons.
好吧 稍安勿躁
Okay, hang on, hang on.
那要如何产生足够的力量融合氢原子？
So how do you generate enough force to fuse hydrogen atoms?
一枚小型原子弹
A small fission bomb.
这就对了
Ah...There we are!
反正需要一颗原子弹 何不继续讨论？
Well, since we're going to need one anyway, can we get back to the business at hand?
你和奥本海默博士最大的歧见…
The isotopes issue wasn't your most important policy disagreement
并不是同位素的问题
with Dr.Oppenheimer,
而是氢弹 对吧？
it was the hydrogen bomb, wasn't it?
身为同事 我们有很多歧见
As colleagues, we agreed to disagree on a great many things, uh,
其中一个就是氢弹计划
and, well, one of them was the need for an H-bomb program, yes.
多谢各位临时前来参加聚会
Thanks for convening on short notice.
我不敢相信
I can't believe it.
我们齐聚一堂
Here we are.
说说看 我们知道什么？
Catch me up.What do we know?
B-29轰炸机在北太平洋上空侦测到辐射
One of our B-29s over the North Pacific has detected radiation.
有用滤纸侦测吗？
Do we have the filter paper?
这是毫无疑问的事实
There's no doubt what this is.
白宫表示有疑虑
-White House says there's a doubt.
他们只是一厢情愿
Wishful thinking, I'm afraid.
那些是远程侦测滤纸吗？
Are those the long-range detection filter papers?
那是核弹试爆
It's an atomic test.
俄国人有核弹
The Russians have a bomb.
我们应该领先好几年 但是…
We're supposed to be years ahead of them, but some--
你们在洛斯阿拉莫斯做什么？
What were you guys doing at Los Alamos?
安全措施不够严密吗？
Wasn't security tight?
当然够严密 你当时不在…
Of course it was.You weren't there.
恕我直言 博士…
-Forgive me, Doctor...
但我当时在那里
but I was there.
现在可以开始设计实际的引爆机制
We can now consider the actual mechanics of detonation.
有任何想法吗？
Any ideas?
我称之为“射击”
I call this "shooting."
把一块可分裂物质射进一个大型球体…
We fire a chunk of fissionable material into a larger sphere
只要有足够力量就能引爆
with enough force to achieve criticality.
大家有什么想法？
What do we think? Anyone?
我一直在考虑内爆
I've been thinking about implosion.
球体周围的炸药向内爆炸…
Explosives around the sphere blast inwards,
压碎可分裂物质
crushing the material.
我想研究那个可能性
I'd like to investigate that idea.
我会通知军火库 让你搞一些爆炸
I'll talk to Ordnance, get you blowing things up.
有进展吗？
Progress?
我也很高兴见到你
-Nice to see you too.
见过英国代表团
Meet the British contingent.
你好 我是克劳斯富赫斯
Dr.Oppenheimer, Klaus Fuchs.
你当英国人多久了？
How long have you been British?
自从希特勒说我不是德国人
Since Hitler told me I wasn't German.Aha.
欢迎来到洛斯阿拉莫斯
Come, welcome to Los Alamos.
学校开学了
School's up and running.
酒吧 一直都在营业
Bar...always running.
我设法减少支援人力
And I thought of a way to reduce support staff.
那是？  -瑟伯尔夫人
Is that-- -Mrs.Serber, yes.
我为所有妻子提供工作
I've offered jobs to all the wives.
行政人员、图书馆馆员、计算员
Admin, librarians, computation.
裁减人力 让家人一起工作
We cut down on staff, keep families together.
这些女人合格吗？  -别傻了
Are these women qualified?  -Don't be absurd.
她们是这里最聪明的人
These are some of the brightest minds in our community.
而且通过安全核查
And they're already security cleared.
我告诉格罗夫斯少将你每晚固定举行
I've informed General Groves you've been holding
跨部门公开讨论
cross-divisional, open discussions on a nightly basis.
禁止举行 权限划分是保密的关键
Shut them down. Compartmentalization is the key to maintaining security--
各部主管而已
It's only the top men.
他们一定会和下属沟通
Who presumably communicate with subordinates.
这些人不笨 他们非常谨慎
These men aren't stupid.They can be discreet.
我不喜欢
I don't like it.
你什么都不喜欢就无法进行测试
-You don't like anything enough for that to be a fair test.
每周一次 仅限各部主管
Once a week.Top men only.
我想把我弟弟找来
I'd like to bring my brother here.
不行
-No.
尼柯斯…
Nichols.
我还没听说我的安全许可获得批准
I still haven't heard that my security clearance has been approved.
还没有  -我们明天要去芝加哥
It hasn't.  -We're going to Chicago tomorrow.
你应该再等等
Well, you should wait.
你知道纳粹领先我们两年吧
You are aware that the Nazis have a two-year head start?
奥本海默博士 你难以获得…
Dr.Oppenheimer, the fact that your security clearance
安全许可并不是我的错
is proving difficult to obtain is not my fault.
而是你的错
It's yours.
但这是你的问题 因为我要去
May not be your fault, but it's your problem.Because I'm going.
有多少人参与这些公开讨论？
And how many people were in these, uh, open discussions?
太多人 权限划分应该是铁律
Too many.Compartmentalization was supposed to be the protocol.
当时是与纳粹进行军事竞争
We were in a race against the Nazis.
现在要和苏联进行核军备竞赛
And now the race is against the Soviets.
除非我们挑起一罗伯特
-Not unless we start it. Robert,
他们开了第一枪
they just fired a starting gun.
他们引爆了哪种炸弹？
What's the nature of the device they detonated?
数据显示可能是内爆式钚分裂炸弹
The data indicates it may have been a plutonium implosion device.
就像你在洛斯阿拉莫斯制造的那种
Like the one you built at Los Alamos.
俄国人有核弹
The Russians have a bomb,
杜鲁门需要知道接下来会怎样
Truman needs to know what's next.
接下来会怎样？核武谈判
What's next? Arms talks.
核武谈判？  -当然了
Arms talks.  -Obviously.
氢弹呢？杜鲁门知道吗？
What about the Super? Does Truman even know about it?
我们有没有向他简报？
Did we brief him on that?
并没有
Not specifically.
我们不确定氢弹在技术上是否可行
We still don't know if a hydrogen bomb's technically feasible.
据我所知这是泰勒提出来的？
My understanding is that Teller proposed it?
对  -在洛斯阿拉莫斯？
Yes.At Los Alamos?
泰勒的设计一向都不切实际
Teller's designs have always been wildly impractical.
你得用牛车拖去 不是用飞机投放
You'd have to deliver by ox cart. Not airplane.
奥比  -抱歉 劳伦斯博士 你想…
-Oppie. I'm sorry, Dr.Lawrence.Do you want to
发言？
comment?
不想
No.
如果氢弹能让我们再度领先
Because if it can put us ahead again,
美国总统
the President of the United States
就必须知道
needs to know about it.
洛斯阿拉莫斯的间谍若已泄密给俄国…
And if the Russians know about it already from a spy at Los Alamos,
那我们就得加快脚步
then we've gotta get going.
你无法证明洛斯阿拉莫斯有间谍
There's no proof there was a spy at Los Alamos.
罗伯特
Robert.
把它放在美式足球场底下？
They put it under the football stadium?
这座球场没在使用
The field's not in use anymore.
这样也好
Just as well.
奥比  -费米博士
Oppie.  -Dr.Fermi.
你怎么样？挺好吧？
Come stai? Va bene?
听说你有一座小城镇
I hear you got a little town.
是啊 去看看
Yes.Come and see.
谁能在那种地方专心思考？
Who could think straight in a place like that? Huh?
大家都会发疯
Everybody will go crazy.
多谢你的肯定 西拉德
Thank you for the vote of confidence, Szilard.
那有必要写进笔记里吗？
Do we really--Do we really need that in the notes?
你打算几时试验？
When are you going to try it out?
已经试验过了
We did.
第一次可控的核连锁反应
The first self-sustaining nuclear chain reaction.
格罗夫斯没告诉你？
Didn't Groves tell you?
没有
No.
一个一个来
One at a time, please.One at a time.
奥本海默博士？
Dr.Oppenheimer?
我去了人资部 他们问我会不会打字
I tried Personnel.They asked if I could type.
你会吗？
Can you?
哈佛大学忘了教化学系研究生打字
Harvard forgot to teach that on the graduate chemistry course.
康登 让霍尼格夫人加入钚组
Condon, put Mrs.Hornig here on the plutonium team.
你为什么去芝加哥？
What the hell were you doing in Chicago?
去看冶金实验室？
Visiting the Met?
为什么？  -你不能…
Why?
因为我们有权利…
Because we have every right--
那是我给的权利 不多也不少
You have just the rights that I give you.No more, no less.
我们是在进行计划的成年人 这太扯了
We are adults trying to run a project here. This is ridiculous.
告诉他啊
Tell him.
我们同意要划分权限
Compartmentalization is the protocol we agreed to.
这太扯了 没人能在这种条件下工作
Enough of this madhouse. Nobody can work under these conditions.
你知道吗 大元帅？我不干了
You know what, Generalissimo? I quit.
真是多谢了
Thanks for nothing.
他走了更好
Better off without him.
你不担心他会泄漏机密吗？
Aren't you more concerned about his discretion out there?
我们会杀人灭口
We'll have him killed.
开玩笑的
I was just kidding.
他恨的是我 不是美国
No, he hates me, not America.
少将 不是每个人都跟我一样有把柄
You know, General, not everyone has levers to pull like mine.
我不懂你在说什么
I don't think I understand.
你不是无视我的左倾过去
You didn't hire me despite my left-wing past,
而是因此雇用我
you hired me because of it.
所以才能掌控我
So you could control me.
我的心机没那么重
Well, I'm not that subtle.
我只是个卑微的士兵
I'm just a humble soldier.
你不卑微更不只是士兵
You're neither humble, nor just a soldier.
你念过麻省理工学院工程系
You studied engineering at MIT.
被你说对了
-Guilty as charged.
我们都开诚布公了 帮我弄到安全许可
Well, now we understand each other, perhaps you can get me my security clearance
好让我为你创造这项奇蹟
so I can perform this miracle for you.
格罗夫斯中将 你任命奥本海默时…
General Groves, were you aware of Dr.Oppenheimer's
知道他的左倾思想吗？
left-wing associations when you appointed him?
我知道有人对他有疑虑
I was aware that there were suspicions about him.
也知道他的极端自由派背景
I was aware he had a very extreme, liberal background.
在你看来 他是否会蓄意背叛国家？
In your opinion, would he ever consciously commit a disloyal act?
如果会的话我会很惊讶
I would be amazed if he did.
你完全相信他很爱国
So you had complete confidence in his integrity?
在洛斯阿拉莫斯 我在那里才了解他
At Los Alamos, yes, which is where I really knew him.
中将 你的安全官是否建议你…
General, did your security officers on the project
拒绝批准奥本海默的安全许可？
advise you against the clearance of Dr.Oppenheimer?
他们不能也不会批准 直到我坚持
They could not and would not clear him until I insisted.
你对他的安全档案…
And it's safe to say that you had a pretty good knowledge
有很充分的了解
of Dr.Oppenheimer's security file.
是的
I did.
我今天只希望你回答一个问题
There's only really one question I need answered here today.
根据目前的原子能委员会法规
In light of the current AEC guidelines,
你会批准奥本海默的安全许可吗？
would you clear Dr.Oppenheimer today?
你有法规吗？
Do you have the guidelines?
根据目前的原子能委员会法规…
Under current AEC guidelines,
你会批准奥本海默的安全许可吗？
would you clear Dr.Oppenheimer today?
物理学和新墨西哥州？
Physics and New Mexico, huh?
天啊 路途真遥远
My God. What a trek.
所以你需要一个联络人
That's why you need a liaison.
我要任命洛马尼茨
I'm appointing Lomanitz.
你不会有事
You're gonna be okay.
这里请 各位
This way, gentlemen.
劳伦斯博士
Dr.Lawrence.
莱斯利
-Leslie.
我想提醒你我们在伯克利说的事
I'd like to remind you what we talked about in Berkeley.
权限划分 我完全理解
Compartmentalization. I understand completely.
谢谢
Thank you.
来自伯克利的问候
Greetings from Berkeley.
我来报告我们的进展并征求各位的意见
I am here to update you on our progress and solicit your input.
但我必须分享一些少将不准我说的事
To do so, I am going to have to share a few things that General Groves told me not to.
抱歉 我说我能理解 但并不苟同
Sorry, General, I said I understood, not that I agreed.
好了
Okay.
各位 言归正传
Gentlemen, to business.
谣言说有间谍…  -毫无根据
There were rumors of espionage at Los Alamos.
在洛斯阿拉莫斯  -未经证实
Unsubstantiated.
我听说有共产党员参与计划
I'm told that there were communists on the project.
并不是故意的  -我只想知道…
We didn't knowingly employ any communists.
他们有没有参与氢弹的讨论
Were any of them involved in discussions of the Super?
我记得你要求让令弟去洛斯阿拉莫斯
I seem to remember you demanding your brother come to Los Alamos.
他那时候已经退党了
My brother had left the Party by then.
洛马尼茨呢？
What about Lomanitz?
他从来不是正式员工 只是联络人
Lomanitz was never employed at Los Alamos. He was a liaison.
尼柯斯上校很清楚安检有多严密
Our security was tight, as former Colonel Nichols well knows.
安检非常严密 但仍有可疑分子…
Our security was as tight as it could be given the personalities involved,
做出一些尝试
but attempts were made.
那是什么意思？
What is that supposed to mean?
我们都看过他的档案
-We've all read his file here.
是不是该谈谈琼塔特洛克？
Do we need to talk about Jean Tatlock?
或是薛瓦利埃事件？
Or the Chevalier incident?
失陪一下
Excuse me.
洛马尼茨在一线
That's Lomanitz, on line one.
你好 罗西
Hello, Rossi.
怎么了？冷静下来
What? Okay, just calm down.
又出了错 洛马尼茨被征召入伍
There's been another screw-up. Lomanitz just got drafted.
我们在打仗 博士
We are at war, Doctor.
别说这种鬼话 尼柯斯 我们需要他
-Don't be an asshole, Nichols. We need this kid.
尽快解决 好吗？
Fix it, will you?
那不是出错
It wasn't a mistake.
洛马尼茨想让放射实验室工会化
Your friend Lomanitz has been trying to unionize the Radiation Lab.
他答应会放弃的
He promised to quit all that.
并没有
Well, he hasn't.
伯克利的安全官担心共产党会渗透工会
Security officer at Berkeley's concerned about communist infiltration through that union, the FA--
我下周会去 我会去见他
Well, I'm there next week, I'll...drop in to see him.
你的最高安全许可通过了
Your Q clearance came through.
你绝对不能和可疑分子继续联络
It's important you not maintain or renew any questionable associations.
博士 你是否认为参与…
Doctor, did you think social contacts
秘密战争计划和共产党有交集有危险？
between a person engaged on secret war work and communists was dangerous?
我认为这种情况现在会更危险
My awareness of the danger would be greater today.
所以你认为在战时…
I mean, it's fair to say that during the war years,
这样的交集可能会有危险
you felt that such contacts were potentially dangerous?
可想而知 没错
Were conceivably dangerous, yes.
说真的…
I mean, really?
公开的共产党员
Known communists?
是这样的
Look...
我的心中很久以来都有很多秘密
I've had a lot of secrets in my head for a long time.
不管我跟谁往来…
Doesn't matter who I associate with.
我都不会谈到那些秘密
I don't talk about those secrets.
你在声明中说…
You said in your statement
你在1943年必须去见琼塔特洛克
that you had to see Jean Tatlock in 1943.
你离开了
You left.
音讯全无
Not a word.
你觉得那会对我怎样？
What did you think that would do to me?
我有写信
I wrote.
有写等于没写
Pages of nothing.
你去了哪里？
Where did you go?
我不能说  -为什么？
I can't tell you.Why not?
因为你是共产党员
Because you're a communist.
你为什么必须见她？
Why did you have to see her?
我离开前她表示她很想再见到我
Because she had indicated a great desire to see me before we left.
当时我不能见她 但我觉得她必须见我
At that time, I couldn't, but I felt that she had to see me.
她在接受心理治疗 她非常不快乐
She was undergoing psychiatric treatment. She was extremely unhappy.
你知道她为何必须见你吗？
Did you find out why she had to see you?
因为她还爱着我
Because she was still in love with me.
你们共度一晚 对吧？
Spent the night together, didn't you?
是的
Yes.
你在我生命中来来去去…
You drop in and out of my life
却不必告诉我为什么
and you don't have to tell me why.
那就是权力
Now, that's power.
我并不喜欢
Not that I enjoy.
我宁愿在你需要时陪着你
I'd rather be here for you as you need.
但你现在有更重要的事
But you have other priorities now.
我有妻小
I have a wife and child.
我们说的不是那件事
That's not what either of us is talking about.
琼
Jean.
你要我来
You asked me to come.
我很高兴我来了
And I'm glad I did.
但我不能再来见你
But I can't see you again.
但如果我需要你呢？
But what if I need you?
你说你一定会回应
You said you would always answer.
无话可说？
Not a word.
你认为那符合安全规定？
Did you think that consistent with good security?
事实上是的
As a matter of fact, it was.
我什么也没说
Not a word.
你后来何时又见过她？
When did you see her after that?
我再也没有见过她
I never saw her again.
我能搭最后一班火车回普林斯顿
I can make the last train back to Princeton.
琪蒂 我什么都跟你说了
Kitty, I didn't say anything that I hadn't already told you.
你今天说的话会成为历史
Today you said it to history, didn't you?
这是秘密听证会
This is a closed hearing.
就算他们不公开记录 你也会
If they don't release the transcript, I'm sure you will.
我宣誓作证
I was under oath.
你去见琼的时候早就宣誓和我结婚
Well, you were under an oath to me when you went to see Jean.
你…
You know, you...
你只会每天坐在那里
you sit there, day after day,
让他们把我们伤得体无完肤
letting them pick our lives to pieces.
你为什么不反抗？
Why won't you fight?
罗伯特 我不会让她出席作证
Robert, I'm not putting her up there.
奥本海默博士 幸会了 请坐
Dr.Oppenheimer, it's an honor.Please, take a seat.
不用了 我只想知道是不是该…
No need, I just wanted to check whether I should talk to Lomanitz
趁机和洛马尼茨谈谈
while I'm here, given your concerns.
这是你的决定 但我会小心行事
Well, I'd say that's really up to you, Professor, but I'd be cautious.
了解
Uh-huh.Understood.
至于工会 我想先提醒你…
Oh, and, um......as regards to the union,
留意一个叫艾尔坦顿的人
I wanted to give you a heads-up on a man named Eltenton.
先提醒我？
A heads-up?  -Yes.
对 他可能值得你留意一下
Just that he might merit watching, is all.
我想知道更多细节  -我…
I'd love to get more details.
我现在有约 明天一早就走
Well, I have an appointment now, and I leave early tomorrow.
你能尽快回来最好
Well, come back as early as you like.
既然你现在没空
Since you haven't time now.
你隔天早上又回去
You went back the next morning.
没错 我必须回去
I did.I had to, really.
这次有另一个人
This time there was another man.
他说他叫帕什
He said his name was Pash.
帕什 你见到帕什上校？
Pash.You met Colonel Pash?
帕什上校 请你读出你的
Colonel Pash, could you please read from your memo
1943年6月29日备忘录内容
dated June 29, 1943?
监视对象的结果显示…
"Results of surveillance conducted on subject
他和更多共产党员联系
indicate further possible Communist Party connections.
他和共产党员琼塔特洛克谈了很久
Subject met with, and spent considerable time with, one Jean Tatlock, communist,
附上她的记录
the record of whom is attached."
监视对象是奥本海默博士？
The subject being Dr.Oppenheimer?  -Yes.
是的  -你没见过他？
Whom you had not met?
当时没有 后来见过面
Not then, but soon after.
他是安全部门主管 我不该认识他？
He's the head of security for the project.Shouldn't I know him?
不 他应该认识你
No, he should know you.
我绝对不会让你们见面
I would never put you in a room with Pash.
为什么？
Why not?
当帕什听到洛马尼茨的事…
When Pash first heard about Lomanitz,
他跟联邦探员说他要绑架他 带他上船
he told the FBI he was gonna kidnap him, take him out on a boat
然后用老俄的方法拷问他
and interrogate him in the Russian manner.
格罗夫斯少将交给我一些责任
General Groves has placed in me a certain responsibility,
就像有一个我不能见的小孩
and it's like having a child who I can't see.
只能远远观察他
By remote control.
所以真的见到你…
So to actually meet you is...
我不会占用你太多时间
I won't take up too much of your time.
没关系 尽管用
-No, not at all. Whatever time you choose.
我对你昨天和某个人的谈话很感兴趣
Mr.Johnson told me of a conversation you had yesterday in which I'm very interested.
我担心了一整天
It's had me worried all day.
我不想未经授权就跟洛马尼茨说话
Yes, well, I didn't want to talk to Lomanitz without authorization.
我感兴趣的不是那件事
That's not the particular interest that I have.
而是更…
It's something a little bit more...
在我看来是更严重的事
in my opinion, more serious.
当联邦调查局指出这种情报
Now, when the FBI pointed out that such information
不会被法庭采信
wouldn't be admissible in court,
帕什就表明不会留下任何活口
Pash made it clear he had no intention of leaving any witness left to prosecute.
联邦调查局劝阻了他 但他就是这种人
Now, the FBI talked him down, but that's the man you're dancing with.
你知道他国对放射实验室的研究感兴趣
I gather you've heard there are other parties interested in the work of the Radiation Lab?
一个隶属苏联领事馆的人
A man attached to the Soviet Consul
通过中间人表示…
indicated through intermediate people to people on this project
他能够为计划中的人传递机密情报
that he was in a position to transmit information.
计划中的人为什么要那么做？
Why would anyone on the project wanna do that?
老实说 我看得出总统可能有理由…
Frankly, I can see that there might be an argument
和俄国分享情报 毕竟他们是盟友
for the commander-in-chief informing the Russians. They're our allies after all.
但我不喜欢用走后门的方法
But I don't like the idea of it going out the back door.
所以稍微留意不会有坏处
It might not hurt to be on the lookout for it.
你跟帕什那么说？
And you said that to Pash?
我只想表明俄国不是德国
I was trying to put it in the context of "Russia's not Germany."
鲍里斯帕什的父亲是俄罗斯正教会主教
Boris Pash is the son of a Russian Orthodox bishop.
他在美国出生 但在1918年
Born here, but in 1918,
回去俄国对抗布尔什维克
he went back to Russia to fight the Bolsheviks.
他亲手杀死过共产党员
This is a man who has killed communists with his own hands.
我的职责不是决定谁该拥有情报
I'm not the judge of who should or should not have information.
而是阻止有人非法泄漏情报
It's my business to stop it from going through illegally.
你能说得更具体吗？
Would you be a little more specific?
有人多次跟我提起一个名字 艾尔坦顿
There's a man whose name was mentioned to me a couple of times. Eltenton.
他是在壳牌石油工作的化学家
Uh, I believe he's a chemist who works at Shell.
他跟他的一位朋友谈过…
He talked to a friend of his
这位朋友认识计划中的某个人
who's an acquaintance of someone on the project.
你觉得帕什就会满意了？
And you thought Pash would be satisfied with that?
我想招出艾尔坦顿 不希望节外生枝
I was attempting to give them Eltenton without opening a can of worms.
我编了牛头不对马嘴的故事
I told them a cock-and-bull story.
你也向格罗夫斯少将说谎？
Did you lie to General Groves too?
没有 我向他承认我对帕什说谎
No.I admitted to him that I'd lied to Pash.
你记得关于薛瓦利埃事件的对话吗？
Do you recall this conversation about the Chevalier incident?
我看过太多版本
I've seen so many versions of it,
以为我很清楚 但现在却更糊涂
I wasn't confused before but I'm certainly getting there now.
你的结论是什么？
What was your conclusion?
他有着典型美国小学生的天真想法
That he was under the influence of the typical American schoolboy attitude
背叛朋友是一件坏事
that there's something wicked about telling on a friend.
原来如此
Well, now...
你能说出中间人是谁吗？
Might we know through whom the contact was made?
那就会牵扯到与此事无关的人
That would involve people who are not to be involved in this.
他是计划的成员吗？
Is that someone a member of the project?
他是教职员 但没参与计划
A member of the faculty, yes, but not in the project, no.  -Ah.
艾尔坦顿的中间人是伯克利的教职员？
So Eltenton made his approach through a member of the faculty here at Berkeley?
据我所知 是的
As far as I know-- As far as I know, yes.
但中间人可能不只一个
But......there may have been more than one person involved.
如果我看起来不愿合作 请了解
Gentlemen, if I--If I seem uncooperative, I think you can understand
我很坚持不让无辜的人惹上麻烦
it's because of my insistence in not getting innocent people into trouble.
你想保护朋友 谁又能保护你？
You're trying to protect your friend.Who's protecting you?
你能保护我
Well, you could.
只要你招出名字
-If you gave me the name.
你命令我 我会照办
If you order me to, I'll do it.
不能这样 你必须自愿告诉我
That is a mistake, Robert.You need to volunteer this name.
他有告诉你吗？  -有的
-And did he give you the name?  -He did.
但当时没有 对吧？  -没有
But not then, did he? No.
而是几个月后 对吧？
No.In fact, it was some months later, wasn't it?
没错
It was.
你认为我很固执
You see me as persistent.
你是很固执 那是你的职责
-Well, you are-- You are persistent, but that is your job.
我的职责是保护为我工作的人
And-And my job is to protect the people that work for me.
而不是让我采取极端手法
Instead of us going on certain steps,
可能会引起你的注意
which may come to your attention...
也会让你感到不安
and be disturbing to you,
我想先跟你讨论一下
I would like to discuss those with you first.
我没在制定计划 只是得了解整件事
I'm not formulating a plan.I'll just have to digest the whole thing.
你前后诘问奥本海默博士几个月
In the months in between your interview with Dr.Oppenheimer
直到他最后招出薛瓦利埃的名字
and his eventual naming of Chevalier,
你是否动用更多资源查出中间人是谁？
did you expend resources trying to find the name of the intermediary?
我动用了大量的资源
Considerable resources, yes.
没有名字会让我们的工作非常困难
Without the name, our job was extremely difficult.
你何时得知这个名字？
And when did you receive the name?
奥本海默终于招出他时我已经走了
I was gone by the time Oppenheimer finally offered it up.
走了？
Gone?
他们觉得我应该前往欧洲…
-They felt my time would be better spent in Europe
调查纳粹原子弹计划的进展
determining the status of the Nazi bomb project.
他们是谁？
Who did?
格罗夫斯少将
General Groves.
他把我调到伦敦
He transferred me to London.
现在开圣诞派对有点早
It's a little early for a Christmas party.
出事了 托尔曼离开了
Something's up.Tolman's been away.
他去了哪？
Where?
露丝不肯说
Ruth won't tell.
嘿！
Hey!
拜托 除了我你还能跟谁说？
Come on, Ruthie.Can't tell me, who can you tell?
权限划分 奥比
Compartmentalization, Oppie.
你凭什么觉得我知道他在哪里？
What makes you think I know where he is anyway?
因为你在重要时刻一向都知道他在哪里
'Cause you do a pretty good job of knowing where Mr.Tolman is when it counts.
像是现在？
Like now?
长官驾到！
Attention!
提早送给大家的圣诞礼物
Early Christmas present for you all.
英国飞行员让我坐在炸弹舱
The British pilots put me in the bomb bay.
教我怎么用氧气罩 但我没用对
Showed me the-the oxygen, you know, but I messed it up.
降落在苏格兰的时候我已经昏过去
When they opened me up in Scotland, I was unconscious.
但我假装只是在打瞌睡
But I pretended I'd been napping.
玩得开心点
Please enjoy your party.
炸弹够大吗？
Is it big enough?
能够终结战争？
To end the war?
能够终结所有战争
To end all war.
海森堡去哥本哈根找我
Heisenberg sought me out in Copenhagen.
真可怕 我的学生竟然为纳粹工作
It was chilling, my old student working for the Nazis.
他为了把我引出来说了一些事
He told me some things to draw me out.
铀的持续性核分裂反应
Sustained fission reactions in uranium.
那听起来像是反应炉而不是炸弹
That sounds more like a reactor than a bomb.
他有没有提到气体扩散法？
Did he mention gaseous diffusion?
他似乎比较重视重水
He seemed more focused on heavy water.
作为中子减速剂？
As a moderator?
对 不是用核石墨
Yes, instead of graphite.
怎么了？
What?
他用错方法了
He took a wrong turn.We're ahead.
我们领先他们 又有你帮忙 尼尔斯
And with you here to help us, Niels...
抱歉 你们能不能回避一下？
Sorry, could you--could you give us a moment, gentlemen?
我不是来帮忙的 罗伯特
I am not here to help, Robert.
我知道没有我你也能做到
I knew you could do this without me.
那你为什么来？
Then why did you come?
讨论以后的事
To talk about after.
你即将制造的力量将永远改变世界
The power you're about to reveal will forever outlive the Nazis.
这世界却毫无准备
And the world is not prepared.
你抬起石头却没想到会出现一条毒蛇
"You could lift the stone without being ready for the snake that's revealed."
我们必须让政客了解这不是全新的武器
We have to make the politicians understand, this isn't a new weapon.
而是全新的世界
It's a new world.
我会尽力鼓吹这一点 但是你
I'll be out there doing what I can, but you...
你是美国普罗米修斯
You are an American Prometheus.
你赋予人类自我毁灭的力量
The man who gave them the power to destroy themselves,
他们会尊重这一点
and they'll respect that.
你的工作这才真正开始
Then your work really begins.
抱歉 奥比 有一通电话
I'm sorry, Oppie, but there's a call.
从旧金山打来的
From San Francisco.
罗伯特？
Robert?
罗伯特 罗伯特
Robert.Robert.
天啊 你怎么了？
Oh, my God.What's the matter?
发生什么事？
What happened?
她父亲打来
Her father called.
他们昨天在浴室发现她
They found her yesterday in the bath.
谁？
Who?
她吃了药…
She'd taken pills.
也留下遗书 没有签名
Left a note, not signed.
她服用镇静剂 但血液中有水合氯醛
She took barbiturates, but there was chloral hydrate in her blood.
有一封遗书
There was a note.
琼塔特洛克？
Jean Tatlock?
我去找过她
We were together.
她说她需要我 而我…
She said she needed me.I...
我跟她说我不会…
I told her I...  -...I wouldn't--
我说我不能…
I told her I couldn't--
都是因为我
No, it was--it was me--
你不能犯了罪…
You don't get to commit the sin
却因为造成的后果让大家可怜你
and then have us all feel sorry for you that it had consequences.
你要振作起来
You pull yourself together.
这里的人全都指望你
You know, people here depend on you.
唐纳德 你想发表意见吗？
Donald, would you like to contribute here, please?
你只能靠自己
You're on your own, pal.
我不会因为钚有放射性辞职
Bob, I'm not quitting my job because plutonium is radioactive.
我们不知道它对女性生殖器官有何影响
We just don't know what it might do to the female reproductive system--
你的生殖器官被暴露的比我的多
Your reproductive system is more exposed than mine, presumably.
别吵了
Can we please?
连内爆装置都没有
The implosion device is nowhere.
凡事不能急就章 拜托
You can't rush everything.Oppie, please.
有急就章和循序渐进 挑一个
Well, there's rushing and there's getting on with it, so, pick one.
内德迈尔在努力工作 泰勒没在帮忙
Wait.Neddermeyer's doing his job. Teller's not helping.
你没在帮忙
You're not helping.
我这几周都在要求爆缩透镜的计算
I've been asking for calculations on the implosion lenses for weeks.
让英国佬计算 富赫斯
The British can do it.Fuchs.
没问题
-Absolutely.
这是你的工作 泰勒
It's your job, Teller.
我正在进行研究
-I'm engaged in research.
研究我们不会制造的氢弹
On a hydrogen bomb we're not even building.
我不会替那个人工作
I won't work for that man.
让他走 他在耍大牌
Let him go.He's a prima donna.
我同意 他应该离开
I agree.He should leave Los Alamos.
好吧
Okay.
基斯 你取代内德迈尔
Kisty, you replace Neddermeyer.
塞斯 我把你调到钚组
Seth, I'm putting you on plutonium.
莉莉 替基斯工作 他需要你
Lilli, you go work for Kisty, because he needs you.
富赫斯 你取代泰勒
Fuchs, you take Teller's role.
我要你专心研究内爆装置
I'm putting you exclusively on the implosion device.
没人能离开洛斯阿拉莫斯
And no one is leaving Los Alamos.
他们不让我离开  -没错
They won't let me leave.
我不会让你离开
No.I won't let you leave.
别管汉斯 别管核分裂
Forget Hans.Forget fission.
留下来想研究什么都行
Stay here, research what you want.
核融合、氢弹 我们会开会讨论
Fusion, the hydrogen bomb, whatever. We'll meet to discuss.
你根本就没空开会
You don't have time to meet.
你变成政客了 罗伯特
You're a politician now, Robert.
你早就把物理学抛在脑后
You've left physics behind many, many years ago.
每周一次
Once a week.
一小时 你和我
One hour, you and me.
把该死的栅栏打开
Now raise this fucking barrier.
你在洛斯阿拉莫斯时就开始研发氢弹？
So the Super was under development on your watch at Los Alamos?
是的
Yes.
但你在战后却否认那个可行性
And yet, after the war, you tried to deny it was viable.
不对 我只是指出技术上的困难
No, no, no.I-I pointed out technical difficulties with it.
俄国进行核弹试爆后你试图终止那计划
Didn't you try to kill it at the AEC meeting after the Russian bomb test?
并没有  -但那是你的建议…
-No. But that was the recommendation of the AEC,
不是吗？  -我们讨论过…
was it not? After hours of discussion
那是最好的回应
about the best response.
一枚氢弹…
An H-bomb
是一颗原子弹威力的一千倍
is 1,000 times the power of an A-bomb.
莫斯科
目标会是最大的城市
Its only intended target would be the largest cities.
列宁格勒
这是大规模种族灭绝武器
It's a weapon of mass genocide.
伊西 在地图这边画个圈…
Izzy, draw some circles on this side of the map
就是他们的目标
where they would target us.
先是纽约和华府  -没错
Starting with New York. That's fair.  -DC.
这是无法防御的攻击武器
It's a weapon of attack with no defensive value.
威慑  -“威慑”？
Deterrence.  -"Deterrence"?
以目前的核武数量来说
Do we really need more deterrence
真的需要更多威摄力量？
than our current arsenal of atomic bombs?
你在10尺或1万尺深的水中溺死…
Y-You drown in ten feet of water or 10,000,
有什么不同？
what's the difference?
我们能溺死俄国 他们也知道
We can already drown Russia.They know it.
现在他们能溺死我们  -只要威胁升级…
Now they can drown us.  -We're just escalating.
我说过泰勒的设计和战时一样不切实际
As I said, Teller's designs are still as impractical as they were during the war.
我们能制造氢弹 你心知肚明
A hydrogen bomb can be made to work, Oppie, you know that.
我们不应该因此投入所有的资源
I don't believe we should commit all our resources to that chance.
那你要杜鲁门怎么让美国人民放心？
Then how would you have Truman reassure the American people?
只要通过国际对核能的控制
Simply by limiting the spread of atomic weapons
就能限制核武的扩散
through international control on nuclear energy.
你是指全世界的政府？
By which you mean world government.
罗斯福总统心目中的联合国
The United Nations, as Roosevelt intended.
我是问杜鲁门该怎么做 对吧？
Well, I asked what Truman should do, right?
世界局势改变了
The world's changed.
威胁不是法西斯主义而是共产主义
It's not fascism but communism that now threatens our survival.
路易斯 你要知道我们若是制造氢弹
Lewis, do you understand, if we build a hydrogen bomb,
俄国人别无选择也会制造
the Russians will have no choice but to build their own?
他们有可能正在制造吗？
Could they be working on one already,
根据洛斯阿拉莫斯的间谍搜集的情报
based on information gathered from a spy at Los Alamos?
洛斯阿拉莫斯没有间谍
No spy at Los Alamos.
没有吗？  -别岔开话题
Gentlemen.Let's not get sidetracked.There wasn't?
我们藉此机会逼俄国让步…
I say we use this moment to gain concessions from the Russians
做出不制造氢弹的承诺
by committing that we will not build a hydrogen bomb.
这样一来就证实氢弹的存在
Thereby revealing its existence.
你似乎早就认为他们知道了
Which you seem convinced they already know.
够了
All right.
我现在要请委员会成员私下开会
At this point, I'd like the committee members
确认我们最后的建议
to meet in privacy to finalize our recommendations.
我不确定你应该坚持己见
I'm just not sure you wanna go down this road.
恕我直言 我们是顾问委员会
Lewis, with respect, we are the advisory committee,
我们要给他们建议
we will give them our advice.
奥本海默博士？我是威廉波登
Dr.Oppenheimer? Hi. William Borden.
原子能联席委员会？
Joint Committee on Atomic Energy?
是的
Oh, yes, yes.
我在战时是一名飞行员
During the war, I was a pilot.
有一晚完成轰炸任务后
One night, flying back from a raid,
我看见像彗星的惊人景象
I saw an amazing sight, like a meteor.
射往英国的V-2火箭
A V-2 rocket headed to England.
我忍不住想像那枚火箭…
I can't help but imagine what it will be
若是乘载核弹头会有什么后果
for such an enemy rocket to carry an atomic warhead.
我们就必须确保不会有这种可能
Well, let's make sure we're not the ones to make that possible.
奥比 你最好别和史特劳斯硬碰硬
Oppie, I don't think you wanna go up against Strauss.
我们同时发言 他们会听我的
If we both speak, they listen to me.
当你发言 他们把你当先知
When you speak, they hear a prophet.
当史特劳斯发言 他们把他当自己人
When Strauss speaks, they hear themselves.
他们会听先知的话
They'll listen to a prophet.
先知不会错 一次都不会
A prophet can't be wrong.Not once.
你不是指控奥本海默破坏氢弹的研发？
Didn't you accuse Oppenheimer of sabotaging the development of the Super?
我不会随便用“破坏”这种字眼
I was never one of those to bandy around terms like "sabotage."
但波登先生会？
But Mr.Borden was?
据我所知有可能
As I understand it, possibly.
他怎么能写出那么详细的起诉书？
How was Mr.Borden able to put together such a detailed indictment?
他不再是政府员工…
He was no longer a government employee,
但似乎能任意调阅奥本海默的安全档案
yet he appears to have had unlimited access to Dr.Oppenheimer's file.
有可能是出于尼柯斯的允许吗？
Might Mr.Nichols have given him access to the file?
或是原子能委员会的其他成员？
Or someone else at the AEC?
那是非常严重的指控 参议员
That's a very serious accusation, Senator.
你想暗示奥本海默博士对美国不忠吗？
Is it your intention to suggest that Dr.Oppenheimer is disloyal to the United States?
我从以前到现在都认为他完全忠于美国
I've always assumed, and still assume, that he's loyal to the United States.
我对此坚信不移 除非有确切反证
I believe this.And I shall believe it until I see very conclusive proof to the opposite.
你是否认为奥本海默博士构成国安风险？
Do you, or do you not believe that Dr.Oppenheimer is a security risk?
讨论！小工具对文明的冲击
当希特勒在地堡饮弹自尽后…
And if I may, when Hitler blew his brains out in that bunker,
就没必要在任何地方引爆原子弹…
it is my humble opinion that there is no need for that bomb to be seen
除了在试爆地点
anywhere except for that test site.
但我们必须认真思考
We at least have to take a moment to think about
是否应该继续研发 因为…
whether the means justify the ends any longer, because--
德国即将投降
Germany is about to surrender.
人类最大的威胁不再是敌人
It's no longer the enemy who are the greatest threat to mankind.
而是我们的研究成果
It's our work.
希特勒死了 千真万确
Hitler is dead, it's true.
但日本人继续作战
But the Japanese fight on.
他们一定会战败
Their defeat seems assured.
对前线的士兵来说不是这样
Not if you're a GI preparing to invade.
我们能终结战争
We can end this war.
该怎么合理化对人类使用这个武器？
But how do we justify using this weapon on human beings?
我们是理论家 对吧？
We're theorists, yes?
我们想像一个未来
We imagine a future,
这个未来想像让我们胆战心惊
and our imaginings horrify us.
人们不会感到恐惧 直到能够理解它
But they won't fear it until they understand it,
而人们无法理解它 直到使用它
and they won't understand it until they've used it.
当全世界得知洛斯阿拉莫斯的可怕秘密
When the world learns the terrible secret of Los Alamos,
我们的研究成果
our work here
将为人类带来前所未见的和平
will ensure a peace mankind has never seen.
罗斯福一直设想国际合作的那种和平
A peace based on the kind of international cooperation that Roosevelt always envisaged.
有何进展？
Progress?
两年内花了十亿美元？
-Two years and a billion dollars' worth?
这很难用金钱衡量
Well, hard to put a price on it.
并不难 把帐单加起来就行
Not really.Just add up the bills.
生小孩完全免费
"Rural free deliveries."
第一年生了80个婴儿
Eighty babies delivered the first year.
今年每个月有10个
This year we've had ten a month.
节育不在我的管辖范围 少将
Birth control is a little out of my jurisdiction, General.
当然了  -少将
Clearly.  -General.
低下头 大伙儿
Head down,
富赫斯 低下头
every--Fuchs.Head down.
看来不错
That's the one.
两次爆破测试 我需要日期
Two viable bombs.I need a date.
九月
September.
七月
July.
爆破正中预定点
That's the sweet spot, gentlemen.
八月
August.
七月
July.
七月进行试爆
Test in July.
但是我需要我弟弟
But I need my brother.
弗兰克了解沙漠 他也不再碰政治
Frank knows the desert, he's left politics behind,
而且和劳伦斯合作两年了
he's been working with Lawrence for two years now.
这场试爆要命名什么？
What do we call the test?
震撼吾心 三一之神
"Batter my heart, three person'd God."
什么？
What?
三位一体
Trinity.
令弟是共产党员 你却坚持把他找去
You insisted on bringing on your brother Frank, a known communist.
前共产党员
Former communist.
你让前共产党员参与…
You brought a known former communist
美国最机密和最重要的国防计划
onto America's most secret and important defense project.
我可以完全信任他 毫无疑问
I knew my brother could be trusted.Absolutely.
你对你能信任谁的判断是正确的吗？
And you felt your judgment was sound on who on the team could be trusted.
富赫斯 低下头
Fuchs, head down.Okay,
大家准备好了吗？
everybody ready.
希望你们得到了教训
I hope you learned something.
我们的距离必须更远
Yeah, we learned we're gonna need to be a lot further away.
尽快计算出距离
Well, figure it out.Fast.
明早要去华府 必须给出一个日期
We leave for Washington in the morning.We're gonna give them a date.
你从芝加哥跑来 利奥
You're a long way from Chicago, Leo.
再不采取行动 他们会用来轰炸日本
If we don't act now, they're going to use this thing against Japan.
杜鲁门本来约见我们 但被人阻止了
We booked a meeting with Truman, but somebody killed it.
你要去见战争部长
You're meeting the secretary of war.
我们在制造它 不代表能决定怎么使用
Just because we're building it doesn't mean we get to decide how it's used.
历史将评断我们 罗伯特
History will judge us, Robert.
我们在芝加哥拟出一份请愿书
In Chicago, we put together a petition.
我不会参与那件事
I'm not getting into that.
说出你的担忧 我会帮你转达
Just tell me your concerns and I'll relay them.
我的担忧？
My concerns?
德国战败了 日本也撑不了不久
Germany's defeated.Japan's not going to hold out alone.
你怎么知道？这是你的主意
How could you know that? You got us into this.
你和爱因斯坦告诉罗斯福应该制造炸弹
You and Einstein with your letter to Roosevelt saying we could build a bomb.
用来对付德国
Against Germany.
制造武器没这么简单 西拉德
That's not how weapons manufacture works, Szilard.
奥比 你得帮忙
Oppie, you have to help.
费米在开会 劳伦斯也在开会
Fermi's in the meeting.Lawrence is in the meeting.
他们不是你
They're not you.
你是伟大的科学推销员
You're the great salesman of science.
可以说服任何人
You can convince anyone of anything.
甚至你自己
Even yourself.
失陪了
Excuse me.
东京大轰炸死了十万人
The firestorm in Tokyo killed 100,000 people.
大多数是平民
Mostly civilians.
发生这种事却没人抗议
I worry about an America
我为美国感到忧心
where we do these things and no one protests.
珍珠港事件和三年的太平洋战争
Pearl Harbor and three years of brutal conflict in the Pacific
让我们得到美国民众的支持
bought us a lot of latitude with the American public.
足以投放原子弹？
Enough to unleash the atomic bomb?
原子弹不会像东京大轰炸那样死伤惨重
The A-bomb might not cause as much damage as the Tokyo bombings.
估计的死亡人数？
What are we estimating?
投放在中型城市…
In a medium-sized city,
2到3万人死亡
20,000 or 30,000 dead.
对 但是…
Yes, but
别低估原爆造成的心理冲击
don't underestimate the psychological impact of an atomic explosion.
一团1万尺高的火球
A pillar of fire 10,000 feet tall.
方圆1英里内致命的中子辐射
Deadly neutron effects for a mile.In all directions.
全都来自一颗炸弹
From one single device.
从高空中的轰炸机上投放
Dropped from a barely noticed B-29,
原子弹将会是…
the atomic bomb will be
神圣力量的可怕启示
a terrible revelation of divine power.
如果是真的 这将是致命一击
If that's true, it would be definitive.
二次大战将会终结
World War II would be over.
我们的弟兄也能回家
Our boys would come home.
军事目标？
Military targets?
没有够大的目标
Uh...There aren't any big enough.
重要的军工厂 附近有工人宿舍
Perhaps a vital war plant with workers housed nearby?
我们可以发出警告 减少平民伤亡
And we could issue a warning to reduce civilian casualties.
敌方会倾巢而出对付我们…
They'd send everything they have up against us,
我会在轰炸机上面
and I'd be up in that plane.
但若是宣布了却没爆炸…
But if we announce it and it fails to go off,
就会失去日本投降的机会
we'd scupper any chance of a Japanese surrender.
没办法展现原子弹威力逼日本投降吗？
Is there no way to demonstrate a bomb to Japan to provoke surrender?
我们打算以最明确的方式展现威力
We intend to demonstrate it in the most unambiguous terms.
两次
Twice.
第一次展现武器的威力
Once, to show the weapon's power,
第二次表明他们不投降就会继续下去
and a second to show that we can keep doing this until they surrender.
我们有12座城市可以挑选…
We have a list of 12 cities to choose from--
抱歉 11座
Sorry, 11.
我剔除了京都 那是日本文化的象征
I've taken Kyoto off the list due to its cultural significance to the Japanese people.
而且我和我太太去那里度蜜月
Also, my wife and I honeymooned there.
那是很美的古都
It's a magnificent city.
让我把事情变得更简单
Let me make this simple for you, gentlemen.
根据我不能分享的情报
According to my intelligence, which I cannot share with you,
日本人民不会投降…
the Japanese people will not surrender,
不管是任何情况
under any circumstances,
除非我们完全占领日本本岛
short of a successful and total invasion of the home islands.
美国和日本都会死伤惨重
Many lives will be lost, American and Japanese.
在日本城市投放原子弹会拯救人命
The use of the atomic bomb on Japanese cities will save lives.
只要我们具有道德优势
If we retain moral advantage.
怎么说？
-How so?
不先通知盟友就使用这武器
Well, if we use this weapon without informing our allies,
会被视为威胁
they'll see it as a threat,
我们就会进入军备竞赛
and we'll be in an arms race.
我们能对苏联公开多少？
How open can we be with the Soviets?
保密不会阻止苏联成为核武国家
Secrecy won't stop the Soviets from becoming part of the atomic world.
根据情报他们没有铀
We've been told they have no uranium.
你的情报错误
You've been misinformed.
俄国迟早会有核武
A Russian bomb is a matter of time.
这项计划在战后必须继续进行
The program needs to continue at full pace after the war.
史汀生部长 容我发言
Secretary Stimson, if I may,
参与计划的科学家并非意见一致
not all scientists on the project are in agreement.
现在应该考虑其他的意见
In fact, this might be a moment to consider other opinions.
科学家…
If you talk--
曼哈顿计划从一开始…
The Manhattan Project has been plagued from the start
就有口风不紧和不忠贞的科学家参与
by certain scientists of doubtful discretion and uncertain loyalty.
其中一个想和总统会面
One of them just tried to meet with the president.
我们需要这些人
Now, we need these men, but as soon as it's practical,
但一旦可行 就该将他们踢出计划
we should sever any such scientists from the program.
你也同意吧 博士？
Wouldn't you agree, Doctor?
如果俄国一定会有原子弹
If a Russian bomb is inevitable,
也许应该邀请他们的顶尖科学家参与
perhaps we should invite their top scientists to Trinity?
杜鲁门总统并不打算…
President Truman has no intention of raising expectations
让史达林参与原子弹计划
that Stalin be included in the atomic project.
告知他我们的进展作为赢得战争的手段
Informing him of our breakthrough and presenting it as a means to win the war
不必做出无法实现的承诺
need not make unkeepable promises.
但是七月的波茨坦和平会议…
But the Potsdam peace conference in July
将是杜鲁门总统进行对话的最后机会
will be President Truman's last chance to have that conversation.
到时候会有实用的炸弹吗？
Can you give us a working bomb by then?
绝对会 我们会在会议前进行试爆
Absolutely.We will test fire before the conference.
观测站位于原爆点9.1公里…
Ground Zero, observation posts at 10,000
以北、以南及以西
yards north, south and west.
从哪里引爆？
Where do we trigger from?
9.1公里以南
South, 10,000.
军事基地位于16公里以南
And Base Camp is ten miles south here.
32.1公里外的山上还有一个观测站
And there's a further observation post on--on that hill 20 miles away.
那是什么？引爆线已经埋好了
What's that, Frank? Trigger lines already went in.
空军要求为B-29轰炸机提供一排指引灯
The Air Force requested a line of lights for their B-29.
轰炸机？炸弹被吊在塔台上
What B-29? Our bomb's on the tower.
他们想要藉由试爆确认安全距离
They wanna use the test to confirm a safe operating distance.
太危险了
That's risky.
在错估爆炸范围下
yards north, south and west.
对日本投放炸弹会更危险
and hoping that we were right about the blast radius.
别影响进度 我们要在15号试爆
Don't let them slow us down.We're firing on the 15th.
15号？那…  -15号
The 15th? That's not-- The 15th.
15号
The 15th.
原爆点南
我会跟弗兰克和基斯在南观测站
So I'll be here at South Observation point with Frank and Kistiakowsky.
你们会在基地、西观察站或是远距观察
You'll all be assigned to Base Camp, West Observation, or Far Observation.
小心点
Whoa, whoa, whoa! Careful with the knife.
小心
There, carefully.
这些距离安全吗？
Are those safe distances?
都是根据你的计算
-They're based on your calculations.
真的该站在你的计算这一边 汉斯
Time to stand behind your science, Hans.Literally.
好了
Yeah.
辐射云呢？
What about the radiation cloud?
没有强风 应该会在3到5公里处消散
Without high winds, it should settle within two to three miles.
疏散措施到位
Evacuation measures are in place.
需要好天气提供能见度 天气一定要好
But we need good weather for visibility, so it has to be fine.
大家都出去
Everybody out.
15号晚上进行试爆
We go on the night of the 15th.
那是期限 有人有话想说就说
It's a hard deadline, so if anyone has anything, speak now.
好了 停下来
Little, little more.Okay, stop, stop.
大伙儿 床垫
Everybody, mattresses.
把床垫铺在底下
Put the mattress underneath.
应该做最后一次内爆试验
Could use a final implosion test.
会有帮助
It couldn't hurt.
做吧
-Do it.
还有什么能阻止我们？
Is there anything else that might stop us?
真的要发生了 对吧？
It's happening, isn't it?
我会传个口信
I'll send a message.
如果试爆成功…
If it's gone our way...
就来收床单
take in the sheets.
罗伯特？
Robert.
祝好运
Break a leg.
奥比只估计3千吨威力
Oppie's taken a very modest three kilotons.
泰勒赌4万5千吨  -2万吨
Teller's in with 45.  -Twenty.
2万吨黄色炸弹威力…
20,000 tons of TNT.
有人想另外赌会点燃大气层吗？
And does anyone want the side action on atmospheric ignition?
你是说必须延期？
Are you saying we'll have to delay?
这样比较安全
-I'm saying it would be prudent.
暴风雨到了试爆地点？
This weather, has it reached the site?
贝特打来告诉你内爆试验失败
Bethe is calling to tell you the implosion test failed.
汉斯 他在这里
Hello, Hans.Yes, he's here.
是的
Yes.
他错了吗？
Is he wrong?  -No.
没错  -没错？
No?  -No.
我们要引爆哑弹？
So we're about to fire a dud?  -No.
不是  -请解释
Explain.  -Well,
我不能解释 我就是知道
I can't.I just--I just know.
我知道爆缩透镜会有效
I know the implosion lenses will work.
我们点燃引爆器 没有引发连锁反应
If we fire these detonators and they don't trigger a reaction,
两年份量的钚就会散落在沙漠
two years' worth of plutonium will be scattered across White Sands.
我用月薪赌你10美元一定会成功
A month of my salary against ten bucks says it lights.
天啊
Jesus.
原爆点风速加快 没下雨
The wind's picking up at Zero, not the rain.
正在打雷闪电
Lightning circling.
你不是应该告诉他们…
You think it might be time to tell your men
远离吊着原子弹的铁塔吗？
to get away from the steel tower with the atomic bomb?
我们去南观测站-叫他们离开
Let's get to South Observation.  -Pull 'em out.
到了那里再决定
We can make our determination there.
大家有两天没睡觉了
The team hasn't slept in two nights.
现在喊停 确保安全 就得再等好几周
If we stand down, make the bomb safe, we won't be back here for weeks.
我们会错过波茨坦会议
Then we'll miss Potsdam.
我七点前得通知杜鲁门 快来不及了
I gotta get word to Truman by 7:00. Our window's closing.
这是什么鬼天气？
What is this doing?
刮风下雨和打雷闪电
Raining, blowing, lightning.
会持续多久？
For how long, damn it?
越来越糟
-It's holdin' strong.
日出前就会停息
It'll break before dawn.
你怎么知道？  -我了解这片沙漠
How could you know that? I know this desert.
晚上会降温 日出前就会停息
Storm cools overnight. Just before dawn, the storm breaks.
他可能是对的 但尽量延迟时间
He could be right, but schedule as late as possible.
5点30分！
5:30.
签名保证 你错了我就处决你
Sign your forecast.If you're wrong, I'll hang you.
告诉大家 5点30分
Frank, tell them all, 5:30.  -5:30.
5点30分  -5点30分
5:30.5:30.
3年、4千人、20亿美元
Three years, 4,000 people, two billion dollars.
如果没爆炸…
Well, if it doesn't go off,
我们都完蛋
we're both finished.
我打赌会是3千吨威力
I'm betting on three kilotons.
低于3千吨 他们不会知道是什么
Anything less, they won't get what it is.
费米说点燃大气层是什么意思？
What did Fermi mean by "atmospheric ignition"?
我们曾经认为…
Well, we had a moment where it looked like
原子弹引发的连锁反应不会停下来
the chain reaction from an atomic device might never stop.
最后燃烧整个大气层
Setting fire to the atmosphere.
费米为什么还在赌这个？
Why is Fermi still taking side bets on it?
算是苦中作乐吧
Call it gallows humor.
你是说如果我们按下那个按钮有可能…
Wait, are we saying there's a chance that when we push that button,
毁灭整个世界？
we destroy the world?
这三年来的研究并不能支持这个结论
Nothing in our research over three years supports that conclusion.
只有非常小的机率
Except as the most remote possibility.
多小？  -机率几乎是零
How remote?  -Chances are near zero.
几乎是零？
Near zero.
光凭理论你想怎样？
What do you want from theory alone?
最好就是零
Zero would be nice.
再过…
In exactly
1小时58分钟…
one hour, 58 minutes,
我们就会知道
we'll know.
天气变好了
It's letting up.
引爆小组离开原爆点 正回来这里
The arming party's left Zero, they're heading this way.
打开开关
Throwing the switches.
发动车辆 准备进行紧急疏散
Turn the cars.Ready for emergency evacuation.
拿片黑玻璃 各就各位
Take your welder's glass. Everybody, take your places.
拿片黑玻璃！
Everybody take a welder's glass!
大家都拿片黑玻璃
Everybody take a welder's glass.
20分钟
Twenty minutes.
还有20分钟
That's 20.
放在腿上
On the leg, please.
费曼  -不用了
Feynman.No.
黑玻璃能阻隔紫外线
For your eyes, sir.The glass stops the UV.
什么能阻隔黑玻璃？
And what stops the glass?
我要去基地 祝你好运
I'm gonna head to Base Camp.Best of luck.
罗伯特
Robert,
尽量不要毁灭世界
try not to blow up the world.
盯着仪表针
Watch that needle.
如果引爆器无法充电
If the detonators don't charge,
或是电压降到一伏特以下
or the voltage drops below one volt,
你就按下按钮中止试爆
you hit that button, you abort.
明白吗？
Understood?
明白
Understood.
两分钟后引爆
Two minutes to detonation.
大家趴下来
Everybody down.
看到山上反射的光之前不要转身
Do not turn around until you see light reflected on the hills.
然后只能通过黑玻璃观察爆炸
Then look at the explosion only through your welder's glass.
90秒后引爆
Ninety seconds to detonation.
Eighty seconds to detonation.
都擦到了吗？
Is it rubbed in?
对
Yeah.
60秒后引爆
Sixty seconds to detonation.
这种事令人心情沉重
These things are hard on your heart.
30秒
Thirty seconds.
引爆器已充电
Detonator's charged.
17, 16,
17、16
15...
14,
13,
12,
11...
Ten...
...nine,
eight...
seven...
six...
five...
four...
three...
two...
one.
我现在成了死神
"And now I am become Death."
世界的毁灭者
"The destroyer of worlds."
成功了
It worked.
你欠我十块钱！
You owe me ten dollars! Oh!
给钱！  -我说到做到
Come on! I--I'm good for it, Kisty.
是真的
You are.
你说到做到了！
Yes, you are!
我们成功了！
We did it!
做得好
Well done.
马上打去波茨坦  -是的
Get me Potsdam right away.
捎个口信给琪蒂
Get a message to Kitty.
我们什么都不能说
We can't say anything.
叫她去收床单
Tell her to take in the sheets.
我们成功了！
喂？
Hello?
琪蒂？  -什么？夏绿蒂…
-Hi.Kitty? What--What? Charlotte.
夏绿蒂 说吧
Charlotte, go ahead, go ahead.
我也不清楚 他只叫你去收床单
Oh, um, well, I don't know, he just said to tell you to "bring in the sheets."
琪蒂？
Kitty?
琪蒂？你还在吗？
Kitty? Kitty, are you still there?
如果在高空引爆 爆炸威力就会减弱
If they detonate it too high in the air, the blast won't be as powerful.
奥本海默博士 我们会接手
With respect, Dr.Oppenheimer, we'll take it from here.
杜鲁门在波茨坦向史达林做了简报吗？
Did Truman brief Stalin at Potsdam?
简报是夸大其词
A brief would be an overstatement.
他只提到一种强大的新武器
He referred to a powerful new weapon.
史达林希望我们用来对付日本
Stalin hoped we'd use it against Japan.
就这样？
That's it?
我们给了他们张王牌 出不出要看他们
Robert, we've given them an ace, it's for them to play the hand.
日标是六号？
You're aiming for the 6th?
这是太平洋战争总司令的决定
Well, it's up to the CO in the Pacific.
我该陪你去华府吗？
Should I come with you to Washington?
没这个必要
What for?
那你要让我知道
Well, you'll keep me informed.
当然了
Of course.
我会尽量
As best I can.
日本人知道我们有原子弹会投降吗
Would the Japanese surrender if they knew what was coming?
我不知道
I don't know.
你看了西拉德的请愿书吗？
Have you seen Szilard's petition?
西拉德对日本人了解多少？
What the hell does Szilard know about the Japanese?
你不会签署吧？
You're not signing it, are you?
很多人都签署了 很多人
Many people have.A lot of people have.
爱德华…
Edward,
虽然我们制造出原子弹
the fact that we built this bomb
并不代表我们比其他人拥有更多权利
does not give us any more right or responsibility
或责任决定如何使用它
to decide how it's used than anyone else.
但只有我们知情
But we're the only people who know about it.
我把我们的各种意见告诉史汀生
I've told Stimson the various opinions of the community.
但你的意见是什么？
But what's your opinion?
一旦使用了它
Once it's used...
核战 也许所有的战争…
nuclear war, perhaps all war...
都不会再发生
becomes unthinkable.
直到有人制造更大的炸弹
Until somebody builds a bigger bomb.
他说会打来
I thought they would call.
今天只是五号
It's only the 5th.
在日本是六号
In Japan, it's the 6th.
夏绿蒂
Charlotte.
打给格罗夫斯
Try Groves.
有消息吗？
Anything?
夏绿蒂？
Charlotte?
杜鲁门在电台广播
Truman's on the radio.
16小时前
Sixteen hours ago,
一架美国飞机在广岛投下一颗炸弹
an American airplane dropped one bomb on Hiroshima...
摧毁该城市对敌方的用途
...and destroyed its usefulness to the enemy.
炸弹的威力超过2万吨黄色炸药
The bomb had more power than 20,000 tons of TNT.
那是一颗原子弹
It is an atomic bomb.
它驾驭了宇宙的基本力量
It is a harnessing of the basic power of the universe.
格罗夫斯在一线
Groves on one.
我们准备尽快彻底摧毁日本的…
We are now prepared to destroy, more rapidly and completely, the Japanese--
少将？
General?
我为你和所有人感到骄傲
I'm very proud of you and all of your people.
一切都顺利？
It went all right?
它很显然造成巨大的爆炸
Apparently, it went with a tremendous bang.
是啊
Well,
这里的每个人都觉得很不错
everyone here is feeling reasonably good about it.
这是一条漫长的路
It's been a long road.
我这辈子做过最明智的决定
I think one of the wisest things I ever did
就是挑选洛斯阿拉莫斯的负责人
was when I selected the director of Los Alamos.
我们花了…
We have spent
二十多亿美元…
more than two billion dollars
投注在史上最伟大的科学豪赌…
on the greatest scientific gamble in history,
我们赌赢了
and we have won.
奥比…奥比…
Oppie! Oppie! Oppie! Oppie!
全世界…
The world...
将永远记得这一天
will remember this day.
现在还太早…
It's too soon to--
无法判断轰炸的结果是什么
It's too soon to determine what the results of the bombing are.
但我打赌日本人并不喜欢
But I'll bet the Japanese didn't like it.
我感到无比骄傲
I'm so proud.
我对你们的成就深感骄傲
So proud of what you have accomplished.
我只希望能及时用来对付德国人
I just wish we had it in time to use against the Germans.
《时代杂志》“原子弹之父”
奥本海默博士？
Dr.Oppenheimer?
很棒的照片
Nice picture.
杜鲁门总统可以接见你了
President Truman will see you now.
奥本海默博士 幸会了
Dr.Oppenheimer.It's an honor.
总统先生
Mr.President.
请坐
Please.
谢谢
Thank you.
国务卿伯恩斯
Secretary Byrnes.
成为全世界最有名的人是什么感觉？
How's it feel to be the most famous man in the world?
你帮助拯救很多美国人的性命
You helped save a lot of American lives.
我们在广岛投放的原子弹…
What we did at Hiroshima was a--
还有长崎
And Nagasaki.
当然了
Well, obviously.
你的发明让我们把国军兄弟带回家
Your invention let us bring our boys home.
那不是我的发明
Well, it was hardly...my invention.
你登上《时代杂志》封面
It was you on the cover of Time.
吉姆说你担心美国与苏联的军备竞赛
Jim tells me you're concerned about an arms race with the Soviets.
是的
Oh, yes, uh...
我认为…
Well, um...
这是我们的机会确保…
It's that, uh, now is our chance to secure...
国际原子能的合作
international cooperation on......atomic energy
我很担心…
a-a-and I'm concerned--
你知道苏联何时会有原子弹吗？
Do you know when the Soviets are gonna have the bomb?
我不确定能够…
I don't think I could give a precise--
永远都不会
Never.
总统先生 俄国有优秀的物理学家…
Mr.President, the Russians have good physicists
以及丰富的资源
a-a-and abundant resources.
丰富？
Abundant?
是的
Yes.
我不这么认为
I don't think so.
他们会投入所有的资源…
Well, they'll put everything they have in...
我听说你要离开洛斯阿拉莫斯
I hear you're leaving Los Alamos.
我们该怎么处理那地方？
What should we do with it?
归还给印第安人
Give it back to the Indians.
奥本海默博士
Um, Dr.Oppenheimer,
如果你关于苏联的说法是真的…
if what you say about the Soviets is true,
就必须扩建洛斯阿拉莫斯实验室
we have to build up Los Alamos,
不是关闭它
not shut it down.
总统先生…
Mr.President...
我觉得我的双手沾满了鲜血
I feel that I have blood on my hands.
你认为广岛或是长崎的任何人…
You think anyone in Hiroshima or Nagasaki
在乎谁制造了原子弹？
gives a shit who built the bomb?
他们只在乎是谁投放的
They care who dropped it.
就是我
I did.
广岛的核爆与你无关
Hiroshima isn't about you.
奥本海默博士
Dr.Oppenheimer.
别让那个爱哭鬼再回来
Don't let that crybaby back in here.
罗伯特发现他的忧虑毫无作用
Robert saw that hand-wringing got him nowhere.
我见到他的时候…
By the time I met him, he'd fully embraced
他完全接受“原子弹之父”的响亮名气
his "father of the bomb" reputation.
而且用来影响政府政策
And he used his profile to influence policy.
《生活》奥本海默
原子能首席思想家
博士 在战后的几年内…
Doctor, in the years following the war,
你是否对美国原子能政策造成重大影响？
would you say that you exerted a great influence on the atomic policies of the USA?
不至于到重大影响
I think "great" would be an overstatement.
是吗？看看同位素的事件…
Really? If we look at the issue of isotopes,
你难道没有逼迫反对出口的人噤声？
were you not personally responsible for destroying all opposition to their export?
一瓶啤酒都能用来制造核武 是真的
You could use a bottle of beer... ...when making atomic weapons. In fact, you do.
我只是发言人 科学界的意见一致
I was the spokesman, but the opinion among scientists was unanimous.
当麦卡锡主义崛起 他知道会被殃及
All along with McCarthy on the rise, he knew he was vulnerable.
他弟弟被全国大学列入黑名单
His brother was blacklisted by every university in the country.
洛马尼茨后来替铁路公司铺铁轨
Lomanitz wound up working the railroad, laying track.
薛瓦利埃则流亡海外
And Chevalier went into exile.
但这没阻止罗伯特逼迫总顾问委员会
But none of that stopped Robert from pushing the GAC
建议军备控制而不是制造氢弹
to recommend arms control instead of the H-bomb.
当杜鲁门拒绝这项建议 他深受打击
He was devastated when Truman rejected their recommendation.
哈瑞杜鲁门宣布氢弹计划
我太想念理查德了
I miss Richard more than I can bear.
我知道 露丝
I know, Ruth, I know.
我很高兴他没活着看到这种发展
Part of me's glad he didn't live to see where this is all going.
寿星来了
Here comes the birthday boy.
洋洋得意  -玩得开心
To gloat. Have fun.
罗伯特 我儿子和他未婚妻很想见到
Robert, uh, my son and his fiancée are desperate to meet
原子弹之父
the father of the atomic bomb, and so...
祝你愉快
Well...good day.
心情不好？
Is this a bad time?
你说呢 路易斯？
What do you think, Lewis?
这对你一定是很大的打击
Well, I think it must have been a blow for you.
对全世界也是
For the world.
全世界？富赫斯对全世界有何重要？
The world? What does Fuchs mean to the rest of the world?
富赫斯？
Fuchs?
克劳斯富赫斯？
Klaus Fuchs?
真是的 你还没听说
Oh, dear.You haven't heard.
英国科学家克劳斯富赫斯
Klaus Fuchs, the British scientist
你让他参与内爆式炸弹研究
that you put onto the implosion team at Los Alamos,
原来他是…
turns out he was
他一直都是苏联派去的间谍
spying for the Soviets the whole time.
很遗憾
I'm sorry.
富赫斯的身分被揭露之后…
After the truth about Fuchs came out,
联邦调查局加强对他的监视
the FBI stepped up surveillance on him.
他知道电话被窃听
He knew his phone was tapped,
去那里都被跟踪
he was followed everywhere,
他的垃圾也被翻遍
his trash picked through.
但他却仍然仗义直言
But never stopped speaking his mind.
他具有坚定信念
-A man of conviction.
也许他以为他的名气能保护他
And maybe he thought fame could actually protect him.
艾森豪上任后 他又看到一次机会
When Eisenhower took office, he saw one more chance.
决定把握机会
He took it.
美国和俄国
America and Russia
可以比喻成
may be likened to
瓶子里的两只蠍子
two scorpions in a bottle,
都有能力杀死对方
each capable of killing the other,
但只能冒着自己的生命危险
but only at the risk of his own life.
这项政策有许多面向…
Now, there are various aspects of this policy--
有很多科学家责怪我 但…
Lot of scientists blame me,
我该怎么保护他？
but how was I supposed to protect him?
…为了保密不肯谈判
...are too secret for discussion,
开诚布公是唯一的解决方法
candor is the only remedy.
华府官员必须开始向美国人民说实话
Officials in Washington need to start leveling with the American people.
那是压垮他的最后一根稻草
That was the last straw for Robert's enemies.
那让他失去他的安全许可
So he had to lose his security clearance?
也让他名誉扫地
And with it, his credibility.
政府怎么能这么对他？
But how could they do it?
他是战争英雄 也交代了他的过去
He was a war hero.He'd already told everyone about his past.
波登又翻他的旧帐
Borden dredged it all up.
波登怎么会拿到奥本海默的安全档案
How could Borden get access to Oppenheimer's FBI file?
尼柯斯给他的？
Could it have been Nichols?
不 他不会那么做
No, I can't imagine he'd do that.
但这掀起了一场腥风血雨
But whoever did unleashed a firestorm
从白宫一直延烧到原子委员会
that burned a path from the White House back to my desk at the AEC.
你也看到他们吧？
You see him in there, right?
我努力一辈子达到今天的地位
I've worked my whole life to get here,
成为美国政府内阁成员
Cabinet of the United States of America,
现在他们要在全国人民面前
and now, in front of the entire country,
狠狠地把我打回原形
they're gonna put me back in my place.
一个低微的鞋类销售员
A lowly shoe salesman.
路易斯 我们可以赢
Lewis, we can win this thing.
我们能让参议院知道你恪守职责
I-I think we can get the Senate to grasp that you did your duty,
虽然非常煎熬
painful though it was.
希尔的证词靠得住吗？
Now, will Hill's testimony back us up?
他不会是问题  -我不认识他
Hill will be fine. I don't really know him,
但他是西拉德在芝加哥的手下
but he was one of Szilard's boys in Chicago,
他们一直不原谅罗伯特
and they never forgave Robert
没有支持反对轰炸日本的请愿书
for not supporting the petition against bombing Japan.
这是轰炸后31天拍摄的
This was taken 31 days after the bombing.
方圆1.6公里的每个人…
Virtually everyone in the street for nearly a mile around
都立刻遭到严重灼烧
was instantly and seriously burned.
日本人提到只要穿条纹衣服…
The Japanese spoke of people who wore striped clothing
身上都留下条纹状的灼伤
upon whom the skin was burned in stripes.
很多人以为自己很幸运…
There were many who thought themselves lucky,
从废墟中爬出来只受到轻伤
who climbed out of the ruins of their homes, only slightly injured.
但他们仍难逃一死
But they died anyway.
他们在几天或几周后
They died days or weeks later from the radium-like rays
因为暴露在爆炸瞬间散发的…
emitted in great numbers at the moment
镭放射线而死
of the explosion.
你在报纸上看到这种屁话？
Did you read this crap in the papers?
一位英国物理学家说原爆
A British physicist is saying the atomic bombings were
不是二次大战的尾声
not the last act of World War II,
而是与俄国冷战的序幕
but the first act of this cold war with Russia.
哪位物理学家？
Which physicist?
你应该认识他
I think you knew him.
帕特里克·布莱克特
Patrick Blackett.
他也许没说错
He may not be wrong.
史汀生现在告诉我…
Stimson is now telling me
我们轰炸已经被打败的敌人
we bombed an enemy that was essentially defeated.
罗伯特 你有这么大的影响力
Robert, you've all the influence now.
拜托了
Please.
请他们继续我对氢弹的研究
Urge them to continue my research on the Super.
我不能也不会这么做
I neither can nor will, Edward.
为什么？
Why not?
不该这么使用我们的资源
It's not the right use of our resources.
你真的这么相信？
Is that what you really believe?
J·罗伯特·奥本海默
J.Robert Oppenheimer.
谜一般的原子弹之父
Sphinx-like guru of the atom.
没人知道你相信什么
Nobody knows what you believe.
你自己知道吗？
Do you? Hmm?
请最后一次欢迎计划主任奥本海默博士
One final time, our program director, Dr.J.Robert Oppenheimer.
我希望在未来的岁月…
I hope that, in years to come,
各位会骄傲地回顾这里的研究工作
you will look back on your work here with pride.
但今天这份骄傲伴随着深切的忧虑
But today that pride must be tempered with a profound concern.
核武若被加入这个好战世界的军火库
If atomic weapons are to be added to the arsenals of a warring world,
有一天世人将诅咒洛斯阿拉莫斯这名字
then the day will come when people will curse the name of Los Alamos.
抱歉 少将
Sorry, Admiral.
我出去买了这个
Stopped off to get this.
《时代杂志》 史特劳斯事件
似乎对你有利
It seems pretty favorable.
文章提到奥本海默
There's Oppenheimer.
标题是什么？
What's the caption?
史特劳斯杠上罗伯特·奥本海默…
Uh, "J.Robert Oppenheimer, Strauss fought...
美国赢了
and the US won."
这样也行
That'll work.
这就是你前几天说的话
Those were your words from the other day.
我们必须掌握先机
We needed to pivot.
你怎么知道《时代杂志》会写什么？
But how would you know what Time magazine's gonna write?
亨利鲁斯是个朋友
Henry Luce is a friend.
你坐在这里让我下指导棋
You sat here and let me tell you how it's done,
却比我早下几步棋
but you've been far ahead all along.
华府的生存法则就是了解游戏规则
Survival in Washington is about knowing how to get things done.
没错
Right.
你是怎么说波登的？
What was it you said about Borden?
他想要借刀杀人
"Why get caught holding the knife yourself?"
我开始觉得你是借波登的刀杀人
I'm beginning to think Borden was holding the knife for you.
最后要看波登对泰勒有多大的影响
It's gonna come down to how much influence Borden's been able to exert on Teller.
我的话很可笑吗？
Did I say something funny?
大家都一直说是波登
Just "Borden, Borden, Borden"
其实大家都知道是史特劳斯搞的鬼
when we all know that it's Strauss.
路易斯把我带到普林斯顿 琪蒂
Lewis brought me to Princeton, Kitty.
然后你在国会面前羞辱了他
And then you humiliated him in front of Congress.
但是比三明治更有用
But more useful than a sandwich.
够狠吧？  -休会十分钟
How'd I do?
也许太狠了 罗伯特
Maybe a little too well, Robert.
那是六年前的事
That was six years ago.
真正会记仇的小人…
You know the truly vindictive,
跟圣人一样有耐心
patient as saints.
史特劳斯清楚表明他的中立立场
Strauss has been perfectly clear that he is neutral.
醒醒吧 是史特劳斯在搞鬼
Wake up! It is Strauss!
一直都是他 你心知肚明
It's always been Strauss, and you know it.
你为何不反抗他？
Why won't you fight him?
老天爷
Christ's sake.
不是尼柯斯…
It wasn't Nichols,
胡佛或是杜鲁门的手下 而是你
or Hoover, or one of Truman's guys. It was you.
你把档案交给波登 让他盯上奥本海默
You gave the file to Borden. You set him on Oppenheimer.
你说服他去…  -波登…
You convinced him to-- Borden
不需要被说服
didn't take any convincing.
慢慢来 用整份档案
Take your time, use the entire file.
写下你的结论 寄给联邦调查局
Write up your conclusions, send them to the FBI.
内容非常广泛 但…
The material is obviously extensive, but
没有新的资料
there's nothing new here.
你会有新的结论
Your conclusions will be.
他也会因此付出代价
And they'll have to be answered.
胡佛把这些结论交给麦卡锡？
Hoover passes them to McCarthy?
那个跳梁小丑不是奥本海默的对手
Oppenheimer's too slippery for that self-promoting clown.
我和胡佛商量好了 他会压住麦卡锡…
I've talked it over with Hoover, he'll hold McCarthy at bay
让你用原子能委员会对付他
while you do this with the AEC.
一场审判？  -不是
A trial. No.No trial.
不开庭 不能让奥本海默公开发言
You can't give Oppenheimer a platform.
更不能让他当烈士
You can't martyr him.
必须有系统地摧毁他的信誉
We need a systematic destruction of Oppenheimer's credibility
让他再也不能谈论国家安全的事务
so he can never again speak on matters of national security.
那要怎么做？
Then what?
弄个小房间 不对媒体公开
A shabby little room, far from the limelight.
一个简单的官僚程序
A simple, bureaucratic procedure.
他要重新申请安全许可
His Q clearance is up for renewal.
把你的指控寄给联邦调查局
You send your accusations to the FBI...
胡佛再寄给原子能委员会
Hoover sends them to the AEC,
你不得不采取行动
you're forced to act.
写一份起诉书…
You write up an indictment.
告诉奥本海默他的安全许可没被批准
You tell Oppenheimer his security clearance is not being renewed.
但是给他上诉的机会
But offer him the chance to appeal.
你也看到 罗伯特 这还没签名
As you can see, Robert, it's not yet signed.
我能留着吗？
May I keep this?
不能
No.
你若决定上诉 他们就得把副本寄给你
If you do decide to appeal, they'll have to send you a copy.
当他提出上诉 相信我 他一定会
When he appeals, and trust me, he will,
我就任命一个委员会
I appoint a board.
他们当然会有律师
They will, of course, have counsel.
检察官？  -实质上是的
Prosecutor?  -In all but name.
谁？
Who?
罗杰·罗博
Roger Robb.
他够狠
Ouch.
他会有审阅奥本海默档案的安全许可
Robb will have security clearance to examine Oppenheimer's file.
格雷的委员会也会有
As will the Gray board.
被告律师不会有
Defense counsel will not.
一场秘密听证会
A closed hearing.
你们对我做出所谓的诋毁性指控…
"The so-called and derogatory information in your indictment of me..."
没有旁听席 没有记者席
No audience.No reporters.
没有举证责任
No burden of proof.
没有举证责任？
No burden of proof?
我们不是定他罪
We're not convicting.
只是否决他的安全许可
We're just denying.
你是怎么说的？
What is it you said?
这只是游戏规则
"This is just how the game is played."
我太天真了
Well, forgive my naivete.
追逐名利的外行人
Amateurs seek the sun...
会被生吞活剥
get eaten.
真正的掌权者不会现身
Power stays in the shadows.
但你现在已经现身了
But, sir, you're out of the shadows now.
所以这一招必须成功
Yeah, that's why this has to work.
是啊
Well...
泰勒今天早上作证
Teller's testifying this morning.
那会有帮助 然后…
That'll help. And then...
希尔下午出席作证
Hill is in the afternoon.
希尔也会帮助我们
Hill is gonna help us too.
总经理KD尼柯斯谨启
你也看到 罗伯特 这还没签名
As you can see, Robert, it's not yet signed.
我能留着吗？
May I keep this?
不能
-No.
你若决定上诉…
If you do decide to appeal,
他们就得把副本寄给你
then they'll have to send you a copy.
用我的车和司机 我坚持
Take my car and driver.I insist.
我必须谘询我的律师 路易斯
I'll have to consult my lawyers, Lewis.
当然了 但别拖太久
Of course.But don't take too long.
我压不住尼柯斯
I can't keep Nichols at bay.
很抱歉走到这个地步
I'm sorry it's come to this, Robert.
我觉得是错的
I think it's wrong.
尼柯斯希望我抗辩 好让一切留下记录
Nichols wants me to fight so he can get it all on the record.
史特劳斯要我退让
Strauss wants me to walk away.
史特劳斯知道你不能退让
Strauss knows that you can't do that.
那等于是承认这些指控
You'd be accepting the charges.
你会丢掉工作
You'll lose your job.
也会名誉扫地
You will lose your reputation.
我们会失去我们的房子
We'll lose our house.
罗伯特 我们必须反抗
Robert, we have to fight.
身为原子能委员会律师 我不能代表你
As AEC counsel, I can't represent you.
我会打给洛伊德盖里森
I'll call Lloyd Garrison.
他很厉害
He's good.
最顶尖的 但…
-The best, but...
我得警告你…
I have to warn you,
这会很不公平
this won't be a fair fight.
你在1943年和鲍里斯帕什访谈时
During your interview with Boris Pash in 1943,
有没有提到微缩胶片？
did you refer to microfilm?
没有  -标记11 第1页 第3段
No.  -Tab 11, page one, paragraph three.
你没说“领事馆有位缩微胶片专家”？
You never said, "Man of the consulate expert in the use of microfilm."
对不起  -没有
I'm sorry.  -No.
我想知道罗博先生引用哪份文件
I would like to know what document Mr.Robb is quoting from
我们也想拿到副本
and if we might be furnished with a copy.
这是机密文件 盖里森先生
The document is classified, Mr.Garrison.
我们应该回到第一手资料
I think we should get back to firsthand information.
这就是第一手资料
This is firsthand.
怎么说 罗杰？
-How so, Roger?
这是访谈的录音
There was a recording of the interview.
我的当事人有可能做出伪证…
You let my client sit here and potentially perjure himself
你却一直拥有录音档案？
and all this time, you had a recording?
没人叫你的当事人窜改他之前的回答
Nobody told your client to misrepresent his former answers.
窜改？那是12年前的事
Misrepres--It was 12 years ago.
我们能听这段录音吗？
Can we hear this recording?
你没有安全许可 盖里森先生
You don't have the clearance, Mr.Garrison.
但你却把它列入记录
But you're reading it into the record.
拜托
-Please, please.
这场听证会是想诱导犯罪或追求真相？
Is this proceeding interested in entrapment or in truth?
如果是追求真相
If it's truth,
公开证据呢？证人名单呢？
where's the disclosure?  Where's the witness list?
盖里森先生 你很清楚这不是审判
Mr.Garrison, this isn't a trial, as you're well aware.
证据法则并不适用 这攸关国家安全
Evidentiary rules do not apply.We are dealing with national security.
是的 但恕我直言
Yes, sir, with all due respect,
国家安全并不能阻止检方…
I fail to see how national security prevents the prosecution
提供证人名单-也许应该暂时休会
from providing us a list of witnesses. Perhaps we are in need of a brief recess.
各位 我向你们保证
Gentlemen, you have my words.
如果这些来自记录副本 我就会接受
If you say they're from a transcript, then I'll accept it.
我解释过我编了牛头不对马嘴的故事
I've already explained I made up a cock-and-bull story.
你为什么要编出这么复杂的故事？
But why would anyone make up such an elaborate story?
因为我是个白痴
Because I was an idiot.
为什么要说谎？
Why lie?
我很显然是不想透露中间人是谁
Well, clearly with the intention of not revealing who the intermediary was.
你的朋友 共产党员哈肯薛瓦利埃
Your friend, Haakon Chevalier, the communist?
他还是你的朋友吗？
Is he still your friend?
是的
Yes.
拉比博士 谢谢你前来
Dr.Rabi, thank you for coming.
你知道检方还传唤了谁吗？
Do you know who else the prosecution has called?
很显然是泰勒
Teller, obviously.
他们问过劳伦斯
They've asked Lawrence.
他怎么说？
-What did he say?
他不打算帮助他们 但是…
He wasn't going to help them, but...
但是什么？
-But?
史特劳斯跟他说你和露丝托尔曼搞外遇
Strauss told him that you and Ruth Tolman have been having an affair for years.
你和他们夫妻住在一起的那些年
The whole time you lived with them in Pasadena.
他让劳伦斯相信理查德因为伤心而死
He convinced Lawrence that Richard died of a broken heart.
那太荒谬了
That's absurd.
哪一部分？  -伤心而死
-What part? The broken heart.
理查德从来没有发现
Richard never found out.
劳伦斯会作证吗？
Is Lawrence gonna testify?
我不知道
I don't know.
拉比博士…
Dr.Rabi,
你目前担任什么政府职位
what governmental positions do you currently hold?
原子能委员会总顾问委员会主席
I am the chairman of the General Advisory Committee to the AEC,
接替奥本海默博士
succeeding Dr.Oppenheimer.
你认识奥本海默博士多久？
And how long have you known Dr.Oppenheimer?
自从1928年
Since 1928.I...
我非常了解他
I know him quite well.
足以评断他的忠诚度和品格吗？
Well enough to speak to the bearing of his loyalty and character?
奥本海默博士是一个品德高尚的人
Dr.Oppenheimer is a man of upstanding character.
而且对美国、他的朋友…
And he is loyal to the United States, to his friends,
以及工作单位忠心不二
to the institutions of which he is part.
吃吧
Eat.
怎么回事？
What was that?
没什么好担心的
-Nothing to worry about.
俄国试爆原子弹后 劳伦斯博士
After the Russian A-bomb test, did Dr.Lawrence
是否问过你氢弹的事？
come to see you about the hydrogen bomb?
你最好去问他
You'd be better off asking him.
我有这个打算
Well, I fully intend to.
你会说奥本海默博士坚决反对氢弹吗？
Would you say that Dr.Oppenheimer was unalterably opposed to the H-bomb?
不 他觉得核融合计划
No, he thought that a fusion program
会影响进度良好的核分裂计划
would come at the expense of our awfully good fission program.
但事后证明并非如此
But that proved not to be the case.
如果两者都能兼顾
In the event, both could be done.
假设本委员会并不认为
Suppose that this board did not feel satisfied that,
奥本海默博士的证词完全属实
in his testimony here, Dr.Oppenheimer had been wholly truthful.
你认为是否该给予他安全许可？
What would you say whether or not he should be cleared?
为何执意指控做出如此伟大贡献的人？
Why go through all this against a man who has accomplished what Dr.Oppenheimer has?
看看他的记录
Look at his record.
我们有一系列的核弹
We have an A-bomb and a whole series of it.
也有一系列的氢弹
We have a whole series of Super bombs.
你们还想要什么？
What more do you want?
美人鱼？
Mermaids?
我认识史特劳斯部长很多年
But I've known Secretary Strauss for many years,
我觉得有必要肯定他对…
and I feel it a necessity to express the warm support
科学和科学家的热烈支持
for science and scientists Lewis has shown.
先暂时休会 除非有要事
We'll break now, unless there's any immediate business.
参议员 我想再次要求…
Senator, I'd like to once again request
检方向我们提供证人名单
that we're furnished with a list of witnesses.
我想提醒候选人我们不一定会事先取得
And I will remind the nominee that we don't always have that information in advance.
我们知道希尔博士午饭后会出席
We do know that Dr.Hill will be here after lunch.
主席先生 下一位证人劳伦斯博士…
Mr.Chairman, our next scheduled witness, Dr.Lawrence,
很不幸得了结肠炎
has apparently come down with colitis.
所以会请威廉波登出席作证
So we'll proceed with William Borden instead.
波登先生 欢迎
Mr.Borden, welcome.
请坐
Please take a seat.
波登先生
Mr.Borden,
你在调查奥本海默博士的期间
during your investigation into Dr.Oppenheimer,
是否得到某些结论？
did you reach certain conclusions?  -I did.
是的  -你是否…
And did there come a time
写信将结论告知联邦调查局局长
when you expressed those conclusions in a letter to Mr.J.Edgar Hoover of the
埃德加胡佛先生？
Federal Bureau of Investigation?
是的  -你在写信之前
That is correct.  -Prior to the writing of the letter,
有没有和任何
did you discuss the writing
原子能委员会相关人士讨论信件内容？
of the letter with anybody attached to the Atomic Energy Commission?
没有
I did not.
谢谢 你有副本吗？
-Do you have a copy of the letter?
有的
I have one in front of me.
请你读出信件内容
Would you please be so kind as to read it, sir?
“胡佛先生钧鉴 此信的目的是…”
"Dear Mr.Hoover, the purpose of this letter is to state--"
对不起 能不能…
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, if I could have a--
你为何拖延时间？他只会读出这封信
What is the purpose of the delay? He's simply gonna read the letter.
主席先生 这是我第一次看到这封信
Mr.Chairman, this is the first I've seen of this letter,
我看到的声明中…
and I see statements here,
至少有一项指控不应该被列入记录
at least one, of a kind that I don't think anyone would like to see go into the record.
这些都是从未提出的指控
These are accusations that have not previously been made.
更不是尼柯斯起诉书的一部分
That are not part of the indictment from Nichols.
我认为不该在这里提出这种指控
Accusations of a kind that I don't think belong here.
证人主动写了这封信
The witness wrote this letter on his own initiative,
列出已经提交给委员会的证据
laying out evidence that has already been before the board.
他的结论是有效的证词
His conclusions are valid testimony,
就像奥本海默朋友提出的正面结论
just like the positive conclusions of friends of Dr.Oppenheimer.
必须公平看待
It cuts both ways.
你拿到这封信有多久？
How long has counsel been in possession of this letter?
我不应该接受你的诘问 盖里森先生
I don't think I should be subject to cross-examination by you, Mr.Garrison.
本委员会成员都看过这封信
Mr.Garrison, given that we on the board have all read the letter,
列入记录不是更好吗？
wouldn't it be better to have it in the record?
继续吧
Let's proceed.
“胡佛先生钧鉴…
"Dear Mr.Hoover,
此信的目的是陈述我的意见
the purpose of this letter is to state my opinion
根据多年来对机密证据的研究
based upon years of study of the available classified evidence,
我认为可能性很高
that more probably than not
罗伯特·奥本海默是苏联间谍
J.Robert Oppenheimer is an agent of the Soviet Union.
以下的结论均有依据
The following conclusions are justified.
其一 1929年至1942年
One, between 1929 and 1942, more probably than not,
罗伯特·奥本海默是坚定的共产主义者
J.Robert Oppenheimer was a sufficiently hardened communist,
自愿向苏联提供情报
that he volunteered information to the Soviets.
其二 他很有可能…
Two, more probably than not,
一直都是一名苏联间谍
he has since been functioning as an espionage agent.
其三 他很有可能…
Three, more probably than not,
在苏联的指示下
he has since acted under a Soviet directive
左右美国军事政策…
in influencing United States military policy..."
抱歉 罗伯特  -原子能情报…
I'm sorry, Robert.  -..."atomic energy, intelligence..."
以及外交政策“  -有人会愿意说出…
Is anyone ever going to tell the truth about
这场秘密听证会的真相吗？
what's happening here?
现在请大卫希尔博士出席作证
We will now hear from Dr.David Hill.
希尔博士
Dr.Hill,
你想发表声明吗？
would you care to make a statement?
谢谢
Thank you.
我被要求针对路易斯史特劳斯作证
I've been asked to testify about Lewis Strauss.
他曾经担任政府高阶职位多年
A man who has given years of service in high positions of government
并以勤奋工作和聪明才智著称
and who is known to be earnest, hardworking and intelligent.
我将表达自己的观点
The views I have to express are my own,
但我相信我的证词将表明
but I believe that much I have to say will help to indicate
美国大多数的科学家
why most of the scientists in this country
希望史特劳斯先生完全退出政坛
would prefer to see Mr.Strauss completely out of government.
你指的是某些科学家对于
You're referring to the hostility of certain scientists
史特劳斯先生的敌意 因为他在…
directed toward Mr.Strauss because of his commitment to security,
奥本海默事件中致力于维护国家安全？
as demonstrated in the Oppenheimer affair?
并不是
No.
而是因为他针对奥本海默博士…
Because of the personal vindictiveness
表现的个人报复心态
he demonstrated against Dr.Oppenheimer.
肃静
Order.
全国大多数的科学家都认为
It appears to most scientists around this country
奥本海默博士之所以饱受抨击和磨难…
that Robert Oppenheimer is now being pilloried
是因为他表达诚实的意见
and put through an ordeal because he expressed his honest opinions.
布希博士 我以为我是为国家服务
Dr.Bush, I thought I was performing a service to my country when hearing this case.
全国没有一个委员会
No board in this country should sit in judgment of a man
应该批判一个表达强烈意见的人
because he expressed strong opinions.
你想进行审判 应该审判我
If you wanna try that case, you should try me.
请各位原谅我情绪激动
Excuse me, gentlemen, if I become stirred.
但我感到义愤填膺
But I am.
希尔博士 史特劳斯先生并未提出指控
Dr.Hill, we've already heard that Mr.Strauss did not bring the charges,
或是参与针对奥本海默博士的听证会
or participate in the hearings against Dr.Oppenheimer.
奥本海默事件…
The Oppenheimer matter
主要是出于路易斯史特劳斯的恶意
was initiated and carried through largely through the animus of Lewis Strauss.
奥本海默曾经嘲笑史特劳斯
Oppenheimer made mincemeat out of Strauss's position
对于向挪威出口同位素的立场
on the shipment of isotopes to Norway,
史特劳斯从未原谅他的这种公开羞辱
and Strauss never forgave him this public humiliation.
他们之间另一个恩怨则是来自…
Another controversy between them centered around their differences in judgment
他们对于氢弹对国家安全的歧见
on how the H-bomb would contribute to national security.
史特劳斯利用人事安全系统
Strauss turned to the personnel security system
企图削减奥本海默的影响力
in order to destroy Oppenheimer's effectiveness.
史特劳斯找到少数野心家
And Strauss was able to find a few ambitious men
他们不但与奥本海默的立场相左
who also disagreed with Oppenheimer's positions
而且嫉妒他在政坛的威望
and envied him his prestige in government circles.
我从以前到现在都认为
I've always assumed, and still assume,
他完全忠于美国
that he's loyal to the United States.
我对此坚信不移 除非有确切反证
I believe this. And I shall believe it until I see very conclusive proof to the opposite.
你是否认为奥本海默博士构成国安风险？
Do you, or do you not, believe that Dr.Oppenheimer is a security risk?
我曾看过奥本海默博士在许多情况下
In a great number of cases, I have seen Dr.Oppenheimer act in a way which was, to me,
对我来说很难理解的行为
exceedingly hard to understand.
我也不同意他对很多议题的观点
I thoroughly disagreed with him in numerous issues,
老实说 他的行为既复杂又令人费解
and his actions, frankly, appeared to me confused and complicated.
因此我认为…
To this extent, I feel,
这个国家的利益应该交给
I want to see the vital interests of this country
我更能理解…
in hands which I understand better,
也更能信任的人
and therefore trust more.
谢谢你 博士-谢谢
Thank you, Doctor.  -Thank you.
对不起
I'm sorry.
你还跟他握手？
You shook his fucking hand?
我会向他吐口水
Oh, I would have spit in his face.
委员会应该会很不爽
Not sure the board would have appreciated that.
你还不够有气度吗？
Is it not gentlemanly enough for you?
我觉得你们都太有气度了
I think you're all being too goddamn gentlemanly.
格雷一定看出罗博的意图
Gray must see what Robb is doing.
为何不阻止他？
Why doesn't he just shut him down?
你还跟泰勒握手
And you shaking Teller's hand.
你不能再当一个烈士
You need to stop playing the martyr.
根据目前的原子能委员会法规
Under the current AEC guidelines,
你会批准奥本海默的安全许可吗？
would you clear Dr.Oppenheimer today?
根据我对原子能法案的理解…
Under my interpretation of the Atomic Energy Act,
那在我1942年雇用奥本海默时尚未存在
which did not exist when I hired Dr.Oppenheimer in 1942,
…我不会批准他的安全许可
I would not clear him today
如果我是委员会成员
if I were on the commission.
很好 谢谢你 中将
Good, thank you, General, that is all.
但我也不会批准任何科学家
But I don't think I'd clear any of those guys.
诘问完毕
That's all.
奥本海默博士并不负责挑选…
Dr.Oppenheimer had no responsibility
克劳斯富赫斯或给予他安全许可吧？
in the selection or the clearance of Klaus Fuchs, did he?
是的 一点也没错
No.None at all.
你今天也不会在听证会上暗示
And you wouldn't want to leave this board with any suggestion today
你在质疑他对美国的忠诚度
that you're here questioning his basic loyalty to the United States
以及他在洛斯阿拉莫斯的行为？
and the operation of Los Alamos.
绝对不会
By no means.
我不希望让任何人有这种误解
I hope I didn't lead anyone to believe otherwise for an instant.
谢谢你 中将
Thank you, General.
我们不该让他们久等
Okay.We shouldn't keep them waiting.
她会来作证
She'll be here.
你真的希望她来？
Do you even want her here?
傻瓜和少年才会自以为了解别人的关系
Only a fool or an adolescent presumes to know someone else's relationship,
你两者都不是 洛伊德
and you're neither, Lloyd.
我和琪蒂…
Kitty and I,
我们都是成年人
we're grown-ups.
同生死共患难
We've walked through fire together.
她不会有事
She'll do fine.
你对共产主义的立场是支持反对或中立？
Would you describe your views on communism as pro, anti, neutral?
非常强烈反对 我很久没接触共产党
Very strongly against. I've had nothing to do with communism
1936年以后就没有
since 1936, since...
在我认识罗伯特之前
since before I met Robert.
诘问完毕
That's all.
记录显示奥本海默在秘密听证会
The record demonstrates that Oppenheimer
并没有受到公正和无私的审问
was not interrogated by impartial and disinterested counsel for the Gray board.
而是受到一位使用
He was interrogated by a prosecutor
狡诈法律诡计的检察官审问
who used all the tricks of a rather ingenious legal background.
你这是在指控秘密听证会容许这种行为
You are charging now that the Gray board permitted a prosecution.
如果我参与那场听证会
If I were on the Gray board,
一定会向那位检察官
I would have protested against the tactics of the man who served, in fact,
针对他使用的诡计提出抗议
as the prosecuting counsel.
任命他的不是听证会委员
A man appointed, not by the board,
而是路易斯史特劳斯
but by Lewis Strauss.
那位检察官是谁？
Who was this?
抱歉？
I'm sorry?
那位检察官是谁？
Who was this?
罗杰罗博
Uh, Roger Robb.
奥本海默夫人
Mrs.Oppenheimer.
你有共产党员证吗？
Did you have a Communist Party membership card?
我不确定
I'm-- I'm not sure.
不确定？
Not sure?
是这样的…
Well--
怎么样？
Well?
我假设加入共产党…
I mean, presumably, the act of joining the Party
要先汇钱才能收到党证 对吧？
required sending some money and receiving a card, no?
是啊
Yeah.
抱歉
Sorry.
没错
Yeah.
那是很久以前的事 罗博先生
It's just it was all so very long ago, Mr.Robb, wasn't it?
并不是  -太久了我都忘了
Not really.  -Long enough to have forgotten.
你有没有退回或撕掉？
Did you return the card or rip it up?
我早就忘记的党证？
The card whose existence I've forgotten?
你的共产党党证
Your Communist Party membership card.
我完全不知道
-Haven't the slightest idea.
苏联共产党和共产党有明确的区别吗？
Can a distinction be made between Soviet communism and communism?
我仍是党员时绝对认为这两者不同
In the days when I was a member, I thought they were definitely two things.
我当时认为美国共产党
I thought that the Communist Party of the United States
关心美国国内问题
was concerned with our domestic problems.
我现在不再这么认为
I now no longer believe this.
共产主义已经串联并遍佑全世界
I believe the thing's linked together and spread all over the world,
我在16年前退党之后就这么认为
and I have believed this since I left the Party, 16 years ago.
但是…  -17年前 我说错了
But-- -17 years ago.My mistake.
但是你说…  -抱歉 18年前
But you sai-- -Sorry, 18.
18年前
18 years ago.
你知道你先生
Are you familiar with the fact your husband
直到1942年仍为西班牙内战捐款吗？
was making contributions to the Spanish Civil War as late as 1942?
我知道罗伯特偶尔会捐钱
I knew that Robert gave money from time to time.
你知道他是向共产党管道捐款吗？
Did you know this money was going into Communist Party channels?
你是说“通过”吧？
Don't you mean "through"?
什么？  -你应该是说
-Pardon? I think you mean
“通过共产党管道” 对吧？
"through Communist Party channels," don't you?
是的  -是吗？
Yes! Yes?
是的  -对吧？
Yes! -Yes.
那是否代表一直到1942年
Then would it be fair to say that this meant that by 1942,
你先生仍然和共产党藕断丝连？
your husband had not stopped having anything to do with the Communist Party?
你不必回答是或否 怎么回答都行
You don't have to answer that yes or no. You can answer that any way you wish.
我知道 谢谢
I know that, thank you.
你的问题有毛病
It's your question.
你的措辞并不正确
It's not properly phrased.
但你知道我想问什么？
Do you understand what I'm getting at?  -I do.
我知道  -那你为何不回答？
Then why don't you answer it that way?
因为我不喜欢你的措辞
'Cause I don't like your phrase.
“和共产党藕断丝连”
"Having anything to do with the Communist Party."
罗伯特从来就没和共产党有任何关系
Because Robert never had anything to do with the Communist Party as such.
我知道他捐钱给西班牙难民
I know he gave money to Spanish refugees.
也知道他对共产主义思想感兴趣…
I know he took an intellectual interest in communist ideas--
是否有两种共产主义者？
Are there two types of communists?
知识分子或是一般的共产党？
Intellectual communists and your plain, old, regular commie?
我回答不了那问题
Well, I couldn't answer that one.
我也回答不了
I couldn't either.
再见
Good evening.
罗伯特 你赢不了他们
Robert, you can't win this thing.
这是有预设结果的不公平审判
It's a kangaroo court with a predetermined outcome.
你为何还要继续下去？
Why put yourself through more of it?
我自有原因
I have my reasons.
好吧
All right.
晚安
Good night.
他说的有道理
He has a point.
我不确定你了解 阿尔伯特
I'm not sure you understand, Albert.
是吗？
No?
我离开德国后再也没回去
I left my country never to return.
你对国家做出伟大贡献
You served your country well.
如果这个国家是这么回报你…
If this is the reward she offers you, then...
也许你应该背弃它
perhaps you should turn your back on her.
但是我很爱这个国家
Damn it, I happen to love this country.
那就叫他们去死吧
Then tell them to go to hell.
有趣的是 这不再是确认听证会
Interestingly enough, this is no longer a confirmation hearing,
而是一场审判
it's now a trial
关于另一场审判！
about a trial!
他说是你发起秘密听证会不是好事
It's not good he's telling everyone you initiated the hearings.
他什么都不能证明
He can't prove a goddamn thing.
更不能证明是我把档案交给波登
He certainly can't prove that I gave the file to Borden.
这并不是法庭
We're not in court, sir.
没有举证责任
There's no burden of proof.
没错 他们不想定我罪…
Right.They're not convicting...
只想否决我的任命
just denying.
希尔为何来抹黑我？他有何目的？
But why would Hill come here to tear me down? What's his angle?
做对的事需要理由吗？
Do people need a reason to do the right thing?
他认为是对的-我说过…
As he sees it.
奥本海默第一次和爱因斯坦见面
I told you, Oppenheimer poisoned the scientists against me,
就策动科学家反对我
right from that first meeting.
我不知道那天他说了什么
I don't know what Oppenheimer said to him that day,
但爱因斯坦看都不看我一眼
but Einstein wouldn't even meet my eye.
奥本海默很会操弄其他科学家
Oppenheimer knows how to manipulate his own.
他在洛斯阿拉莫斯误导天真的科学家
And at Los Alamos, he preyed on the naivete of scientists
让他们以为能够掌控他们的研究成果
who thought they'd get a say in how we used their work.
但他从来不觉得自己有那么天真
Don't ever think he was that naive himself.
博士
Doctor.
你在研究氢弹的过程中
During your work on the hydrogen bomb,
曾否因为道德疑虑退却？
were you deterred by any moral qualms?
当然了
Yes, of course.
但你仍继续研究 对吧？
But you still got on with your work, didn't you?
对 这是探索性研究 不是武器研制
Yes, because this was work of exploration.It was not the preparation of a weapon.
所以比较像是学术研究
You mean it was more of an academic excursion?
不 能否制造氢弹不是学术研究
No, it is not an academic thing whether you can build a hydrogen bomb.
而是攸关生死的问题
It's a matter of life and death.
你在1942年积极推动…
By 1942, you were actively pushing
氢弹的研制 不是吗？
the development of the hydrogen bomb, weren't you?
推动并不正确 我只是支持和研究
Pushing's not the right word.Supporting it and working on it, yes.
你的道德疑虑在何时强烈到…
So when did these moral qualms become so strong
让你积极反对氢弹的研制？
that you actively opposed the development of the hydrogen bomb?
当有人建议政府政策应转向…
When it was suggested that it be the policy of the United States
不惜任何代价制造氢弹
to make these things at all cost,
却无视它和核弹这类武器
without regard to the balance between these weapons
与军备之间的平衡
and atomic weapons as part of our arsenal.
这与道德疑虑何干？
What do moral qualms have to do with that?
这与道德疑虑何干？  -没错
What do moral qualms have to do with it? Yes.
奥本海默想独占核武
Oppenheimer wanted to own the atomic bomb.
成为能够毁天灭地的人
He wanted to be the man who moved the Earth.
他谈到要完全消弭核武的威胁
He talks about putting the nuclear genie back in the bottle.
但是我非常了解罗伯特·奥本海默
Well, I'm here to tell you that I know J.Robert Oppenheimer,
如果他能重新来过 还是会做同样的事
and if he could do it all over, he'd do it all the same.
你知道他从来没对广岛感到后悔吗？
You know he's never once said that he regrets Hiroshima?
他会再做一遍 为什么？
He'd do it all over.Why?
因为那让他成为史上最重要的人
Because it made him the most important man who ever lived.
我们已经任意使用原子弹…
Well, we've freely used the atomic bomb--
事实是你协助军方挑选…
In fact, Doctor, you assisted in selecting the target
向日本投放原子弹的城市 对吧？
to drop the atomic bomb on Japan, didn't you?
是的  -那你就知道
Yes.  -Then you knew, did you not,
将原子弹投放在你挑选的城市
that by dropping that atomic bomb on the target you selected,
会导致成千上万平民伤亡 对吧？
that thousands of civilians would be killed or injured, is that correct?
是的 但没有预期的多
Yes, not as many as turned out--
伤亡人数到底是多少？
Oh.Well, how many were killed or injured?
7万  -7万是指广岛…
70,000. 70,000 at both Hiroshima and--
各有11万
110,000 at both.
在轰炸的当天？
On the day of each bombing?
是的  -之后的几周和几年呢？
Yes.  -And in the weeks and years that followed?
估计大约在5万和10万之间
It has been put at somewhere between 50,000 and 100,000.
至少有22万人死亡？  -是的
220,000 dead, at least.  -Yes.
你感到内疚吗？
Any moral scruples about that?
非常内疚
Terrible ones.
但是你却作证说轰炸广岛非常成功
Yet you testified in here that the bombing of Hiroshima was very successful.
技术上的成功
Technically successful.
技术上来说非常成功
-Oh! Technically, it was very successful.
而且也帮助终结了战争
And it is also alleged to have helped end the war.
你会支持在广岛投放氢弹吗？
Would you have been supportive of the dropping of a hydrogen bomb on Hiroshima?
那完全没道理
That would make no sense at all.
为什么？  -目标太小了
-Why? The target is too small.
假设日本有一个目标…
Well, supposing there had been a target in Japan big enough
大到可以投放热核武 你会反对吗？
for a thermonuclear weapon, would you have been opposed to the dropping of it?
这不是我曾面对的问题…
This was not a problem with which I was confronted--
我现在要逼你面对
I'm confronting you with it now, sir.
这都是他的盘算
It was all part of his plan.
他想为自己塑造出深感内疚…
He wanted the glorious, insincere guilt of the self-important
自以为是圣人的形象
to wear like a fucking crown.
才会说 “不能走上这条不归路”
Say, "No, we cannot go down this road,"
虽然他知道这是必要的
even as he knew we'd have to.
你会因为良心不安反对在日本
Would you have been opposed to the dropping... ...of a thermonuclear weapon on Japan
投下氢弹吗？  -我相信我会
because of moral scruples? Yes, I believe I would, sir.
你曾因为良心不安反对在广岛
Did you oppose the dropping of an atomic bomb on Hiroshima
投下原子弹吗？
because of moral scruples?
我们提出我们的论点…
We set forth our arg--
是你 我说的是你
-No, you. I'm asking you. You!
我提出…  -我说的是你！
-I set-- I set forth
有人反对投放原子弹 但我并不支持
our arguments against dropping it, but I did not endorse them.
你是说三年来夜以继日制造出原子弹
You mean after working night and day for three years building the bomb,
你却反对使用它
you then argued against the use of it.
战争部长问我科学家的意见是什么
I was asked by the secretary of war what the views of scientists were.
我给了他赞成与反对的意见
I gave him the views against and the views for.
你支持在日本投放原子弹
You supported the dropping of the atom bomb on Japan.
“支持” 是什么意思？
What do you mean, "support"?
你说的 “支持” 是什么意思？
-You supported it.
你帮忙挑选目标 不是吗？
You helped pick the target, didn't you?  -I did my job.
那是我的工作 我并不负责做出决策
I was not in a policy-making position at Los Alamos.
当时我被要求做的事我都会去做
I would have done anything I was asked to do.
那你也会制造氢弹 不是吗？
Then you would have built the H-bomb too, wouldn't you?
我不能  -我不是那么问你！
I couldn't.  -I didn't ask you that, Doctor.
你在苏联试爆核弹后撰写的…
And the GAC report, which you co-authored after the Soviet atomic test,
总顾问委员会报告中说不该制造氢弹！
said a Super bomb should never be built.
我们 我的意思是…
What we meant-- What I meant was--
到底是谁？  -我的意思是…
What you? Who? Who?  -What I meant--
难道苏联不会不择手段增加武力吗？
And wouldn't the Russians do anything to increase their strength?
我们制造氢弹 他们也必须跟进
If we did it, they would have to do it.
我们只会助长他们的企图心
Our efforts would only fuel their efforts,
就像原子弹一样
just as it had with the atomic bomb.
“就像原子弹一样” 一点都没错！
"Just as it had with the atomic bomb," exactly!
1945年不会内疚 1949年却深感内疚
No moral scruples in 1945, plenty in 1949.
奥本海默博士
Dr.Oppenheimer...
你反对氢弹的强烈道德感…
when did your strong moral convictions develop
是从何时开始有的？
with respect to the hydrogen bomb?
当我清楚知道…
When it became clear to me...
人类会使用拥有的任何武器
that we would tend to use any weapon we had.
罗伯特·奥本海默成为烈士
J.Robert Oppenheimer the Martyr.
我让他成为他想成为的人
I gave him exactly what he wanted.
因为研发原子弹留名青史
To be remembered for Trinity,
而不是因为广岛
not Hiroshima.
不是因为长崎
Not Nagasaki.
他应该感谢我
He should be thanking me.
他并不感谢你
Well, he's not.
我还有足够的同意票
Do we still have enough votes,
或是我政治生涯的巅峰
or is the crowning moment of my career
即将成为我一生中最大的羞辱？
about to become the most public humiliation of my life?
参议院即将投票
Full Senate's about to vote.
你会勉强过关
You'll scrape through.
太好了 召开记者会吧
Great, then gather the fucking press.
罗伯特·奥本海默博士
Dr.J.Robert Oppenheimer.
本委员会听取了你的证词
This board, having heard testimony from you
你目前和前任同事的证词
and many of your current and former colleagues,
一致认为你是一名忠诚的公民
has come to the unanimous conclusion that you are a loyal citizen.
但是有监于你持续与共产党之间的关系
However, in the light of your continuing associations
并且藐视这个国家的安全机构
and disregard for the security apparatus of this country,
加上你对于氢弹计划令人不安的行为
together with your somewhat disturbing conduct on the hydrogen bomb program,
以及你对本委员会的回应不够坦承
and the regrettable lack of candor in certain of your responses to this board,
我们以二比一的票数…
we have voted two-to-one
否决恢复你的安全许可
to deny the renewal of your security clearance.
书面报告 加上艾凡斯对此决定的异议
A full written opinion, with a dissent from Mr.Evans,
将完整地提交给原子能委员会
will be issued to the AEC in the coming days.
散会
That is all.
高登…  -罗杰
Gordon.
罗伯特
Robert.
不要去收床单
Don't, uh...Don't take in the sheets.
先生
Sir.
两分钟
-Two minutes...
你们会有机会发问
You'll get your shot.
我们等了很久
We waited a long time
出来吧  -先生！
Come on out! - Sir!
已成定局了吗？
Is it official?
有几张没想到的反对票
Well, there were a couple of unexpected holdouts.
我被否决了 对吧？
I'm denied.Yeah?
恐怕是的  -好吧
I'm afraid so, sir.All right.
谁投反对票？
Who were the holdouts?
有三个人
Um...There were three,
来自麻省的初任参议员带头
led by the junior senator from Massachusetts.
一个想出名的年轻人
Young guy trying to make a name for himself,
不喜欢你对奥本海默做的事
didn't like what you did to Oppenheimer.
他叫什么名字？
What's his name?
甘迺迪  约翰·甘迺迪
Uh, Kennedy.John F.Kennedy.
琪蒂？
Kitty?
你认为你让他们公开抹黑你…
Did you think that if you let them tar and feather you,
世人就会原谅你？
that the world would forgive you?
不会的
It won't.
等着瞧吧
We'll see.
该死
Goddamn it.
你明明说我会过关
You told me I'd be okay.
我没掌握所有的事实 对吧？
Yeah, well, I didn't have all the facts, did I?
这才是事实
Here's a fact.
艾森豪总统去年亲自为我别上自由勋章
President Eisenhower pinned the Medal of Freedom on my chest last year,
因为我一直都以国家利益为优先
'cause I've always done what's right for this country.
他们不想让我进入内阁？
They don't want me in the Cabinet room?
好吧 无所谓
Oh, that's--That's fine.
也许他们应该邀请奥本海默入阁
Maybe they should just invite Oppenheimer instead.
也许他们会
Maybe they will.
我说过 他让每个科学家跟我作对
I told you, he turned the scientists against me one by one,
先是爱因斯坦 我跟你说过
starting with Einstein. I told you about Einstein.
我看到他在池塘旁边
I saw him by the pond.
你是说过 但你要知道
You did, but you know, sir,
既然没人知道他们那天聊了什么…
since nobody really knows what they said to each other that day,
也许他们完全没聊到你？
is it possible they didn't talk about you at all?
也许他们聊的是…
Is it possible they spoke about something
更重要的事？
more important?
史特劳斯先生！
Mr.Strauss!
谢谢谢谢谢谢谢谢
Thank you.
阿尔伯特
Albert.
当下的焦点人物
The man of the moment.
你为我办过一场欢迎会
You once held a reception for me.
在伯克利 你颁给我一个奖项
In Berkeley.You gave me an award, mmm?
没错
Yes.
你们都以为我已经搞不懂我发明的理论
You all thought that I had lost the ability to understand what I'd started.
那个奖项不是颁给我 而是颁给你们
So, the award really wasn't for me. It was for all of you, hmm?
现在轮到你…
Now it's your turn
必须面对你的成就造成的后果
to deal with the consequences of your achievement.
有一天 当他们决定不再惩罚你
And one day, when they've punished you enough...
就会请你吃鲑鱼和马铃薯沙拉
they'll serve you salmon and potato salad.
发表演讲…
Make speeches...
美国总统徽章
颁给你一枚勋章
...give you a medal.
你好 弗兰克
Hello, Frank.
你很幸福 我替你高兴
You're happy, I'm happy.
拍拍你的背 原谅你做的事
Pat you on the back, tell you all is forgiven.
但是要记住…
Just remember...
那不是为了你
it won't be for you.
而是为了他们的形象
It'll be for them.
阿尔伯特
Albert.
当我带着那些计算结果来找你
When I came to you with those calculations,
我们以为会引发连锁反应
we thought we might start a chain reaction
毁灭整个世界
that would destroy the entire world?
我记得很清楚
Mmm.I remember it well.
怎么了？
What of it?
我相信我们做到了
I believe we did.